Hey,
hey,
Heat.
Hello and welcome back to the Ask Abig
show. This is the first episode of this
new year 2026. So I wish you all a very
happy 2026
and I hope you're all doing great. And
in this episode we're going to discuss
history and geopolitics. We'll start
with geopolitics. Today is a great day
for freedom and human rights and
democracy as we all know. So we'll
discuss that and I'll take other
questions as well that you all have
asked in the comments. So as you all
know hopefully the Ask a Widget show is
the objective the purpose of the Ask a
Bidget show is to understand the world
that we live in through the three
primary lenses of history, geopolitics
and science. And today we're going to
discuss geopolitics and history. So
before I start the questions and
answers, let me see who all is there on
the live chat. I can see Vin Ran 5 who
is a new member. Vin Ran, thank you very
much for becoming a member and welcome
to the membership of this channel. Thank
you very much. I can see Geopolitical
Dubai from Indor. Good evening. Rian Sha
from New York. Good morning. Mac 4 J1U I
am confused is here. Anonymous R7U5T
Shatabish
Shatabish Achinta Anand Namaskar. Real
Vladimir Putin Dirana Shanks Buesses
Diran Shanks son Ashini Aush Singh Pam
uh Daksh Valwad once again Swami is here
commando256
Dm Pande Akshai Bharadwaj Krishna of the
Surabies Netherlands hello good to have
you Nirvana Shanks once again online
Mahadev Aishek Shukla live Venezuela
gone
uh anime
Bharata is here from can from
California. Uh Shiradia
namaste Shahad Shared Subadra Subadra
Takina T8G
Swami from Jaipur. Sager Gary hello the
Baron Zemo hello and namaste. Animeish
from again from California. Albvin
Rodriguez, hello. Pankage Dagger. Uh,
Prrenit Kumar, Mystic SK, Jri Krishna.
Um, Part Shiv Shri Shastav from X. Part
is watching from X. Hello. Udbav Sharma
Rahul Dun Namaskar. Anonymous scientist.
Bonjour. Manisha Kardo. Namaste. G. Um,
Sujit Shanak Sha namaskarum. Sam the
gamer. Happy new year. Uh Shatabesh
Surya Pratab no war peacemaker
hello good to have you. Uh Vignesh is
here. Vignesh Kohli from Nav'i Mumbai.
Dorji is here from Nagaland. Good to see
you. Um and welcome Chetananya Manuja
Shiv Shivanch Shivanch Shankar Ritij
Rian Sa Sha the little Kim. Hello
comrade Ara Alvin Rodriguez once again
uh Guten Abend indeed Himmanu Rajit from
Chennai Amisha Mishra good to see you
ma'am sit too look at her online uh
Naneshwar Raju Surya Palenav
Sentinel spy Sandy hello commando situ
once again um it's it's an okay it's anj
Good evening crash and rise bonjour. Uh
Levi Acriman, hello. Good to see you
after a while. Good to see you. I hope
you're doing good. Plank Cog Rituj and
so many other people. I won't be able to
greet you all individually but hello.
Good to have you. Thank you so much.
Pankage is here from Prague in the Czech
Republic. Priyanka Javalia. Namaste.
Okay. Okay. Let's get going with the
questions. What are the questions? What
do we have? Where do we begin? I suppose
we should begin with well the the
question that we should all begin with
which is this one. This is by Argentina
Paro from Facebook. I live stream on
Facebook too. Uh the question is what do
you think will happen to the rest of the
Latin American countries that are
aligned with Maduro's government in
Venezuela if the United States manages
to overthrow that government? Do you
think the left will weaken? Well, the
United States has indeed now overthrown
that government. So, this happened just
a few hours ago. It is still nighttime
there. And what's happened is that the
the United States military has gone in
and uh all the you had all these clips
on social media of the US uh you know
launching air strikes uh on on Karakas
the Venezuelan capital and then uh Shri
Donald Trump G he has announced that uh
they have abducted or captured rather uh
the president of Venezuela Mr. Nicolola
Nicolas Maduro and apparently he is
being taken to the United States where
he will stand trial a free and fair
trial according to the laws of the
United States right so apparently now
the laws of the United States apply
everywhere at least in the western
hemisphere apparently right so they went
in it it's reminiscent of what the
Americans did in the 1980s to Nicaragua
Nicaragua Nicaragua when I was a kid in
the 80s was 80s or 90s, whenever it was,
the Americans went in and they they they
abducted uh Manuel Noriega, who was the
person the the person who ruled uh
Nicaragua at the time, and they took him
to the United States and they charged
him with drugs and whatnot, uh drug
trafficking and whatever else, I
suppose, terrorism, drug trafficking,
etc., etc. And they put him behind bars
and I suppose he is still behind bars
somewhere in the United States. So
that's what they've done to Venezuela.
So the question is what's the deal?
What's going on? What's going to happen
now? Right. So understand the and what's
the importance of all of all of this
this very rapidly evolving situation
geopolitically not just in the western
hemisphere not just for Venezuela, not
just for Latin America, not just for the
US, but for other nations, India,
Russia, China, Asia, etc. What's the
implications?
So
where do we begin this discussion? Let
us begin by talking about the Monroe
doctrine and then the Trump corery to
the Monro doctrine. So what is the Monro
doctrine? It it it was a 19 it was an
American foreign policy. Okay. And it
declared that the Americas, North and
South America, the Americas totally
cumulatively were now closed to European
colonization
and that any further European
interference in the Western Hemisphere
would be treated as a hostile act
against the United States. Okay, that is
1823, 19 early 19th century. That's when
the Americans you know started this
foreign policy and they pursued this
foreign policy vigorously. Uh initially
they were not very powerful but
eventually yeah they were able to impose
this all over the western hemisphere. So
the 2025 national security national
security strategy of the US this
document which has been published the
unclassified version says that the US is
going to revert to the Monroe doctrine
with a Trump corollery on top of it. So
what is this Trump corollery to the
Monro doctrine? So it's it's this new
interpretation of the of the Monro
doctrine. It extends the Monro doctrine.
It says that the US now has the right is
going to assert the right to police the
western hemisphere against extra
regional powers like Europe, China,
Russia, whoever else. and even against
regional actors like uh the drug cartels
and anyone who indulges in any you know
drug activity etc. You can allege this
about anybody. So by doing this the US
will preserve its dominance over the
region, the western hemisphere and it's
going to ensure the security of the
region. So that is the Trump corollary
that has been published last year just a
few months ago. So the Monro doctrine is
now back in force with an extension
called the Trump corollery. So now uh
what's the justification for the
invasion of Venezuela and the uh regime
change that they have affected and the
the abduction of Maduro etc. So it's all
about democracy, human rights. Uh the US
faces national security threats from
Venezuela because of Venezuela's alleged
involvement with uh with Iran as well as
Russia and China. These two evil
nations, right? And of course there's
this Nobel Prize Nobel Peace Prize
winner Maria Machado who is waiting to
take over right just like Muhammadus
took over in in in Bangladesh East
Pakistan right so that's the narrative
and obviously Trump Trump has claimed
that Venezuela has taken over American
oil in some way so Venezuela a few years
ago it nationalized the oil industry
okay but it it did not steal anyone's I
mean by when you when you nationalize an
industry, it means you buy up all the
companies that are operating in that
industry in your country. You don't
capture the companies, you buy them out.
So that's what Venezuela had done. And
the oil that exists on Venezuelan
territory, how is it American oil? I'm
not sure. But that's the justification
that Trump has given.
So uh see obviously it means that the US
actions aren't about democracy, human
rights, freedom, peace, etc. Right? It's
all about controlling oil. Venezuela
accounts for about 20% of the world's
proven oil resources. This is about
controlling oil. It's about controlling
the other resources that you have in
Venezuela. Lithium, gold, rare earth
minerals, etc. Okay. So, uh that's what
it's about. So, when so Maduro has been
arrested, he will stand trial on
criminal charge charges in the US and uh
that's the situation. Now understand the
the importance and and value of
Venezuela geopolitically and from from a
resource perspective etc. See
Venezuela's share of the world's proven
oil resources or reserves is about 80 to
18 to 20%. Let's say 1ifth of the entire
world's
proved oil reserves are in Venezuela.
Immensely important, immensely vital. So
if in the future in a few months let's
say the US tries to invade Iran
hypothetical completely hypothetical
scenario
then there could be a major shock in the
global oil supply because Iran is kind
of the epicenter that region the West
Asia region is the epicenter of of of
the world's oil and energy supplies.
Yeah. So if there is an attempted
American invasion of Iran and there's
this global oil shock, you know, that
oil oil supplies are disrupted for weeks
perhaps, then if the US has Venezuela,
then it's going to be secure and it's it
can it'll be able to control uh oil
supplies throughout the world. It'll be
able to decide who gets oil, who doesn't
get oil. So that's great. That's
fantastic. And so Venezuela, it's about
1/5if of the global oil resources. And
the past 5 years, let's say 2020 to
2025, between 65 to 80% of Venezuela's
oil exports have gone to China. Okay? 65
to 80% depending on the year, up and
down, up and down. So at the higher at
the higher end, it's 80% of Venezuela's
oil exports going to China. Now, China
um you know, China doesn't import oil
only from Venezuela. Obviously, Russia
and Saudi Arabia, these two countries
each account for 15 to 20% of China's
oil imports. So, if Russia is 15 and
Saudi Arabia is 15, that's 30%. If it's
2020, it's 40%. That sort of thing. And
then you have Malaysia, Iraq, Oman, um
etc., which also uh and if you put China
if you put Russia and Saudi Arabia in
addition to these countries that's about
twothirds of China's oil imports. So
Russia and Saudi Arabia are the top two
suppliers for China. Then you have Iraq,
UAE, Brazil, Oman, Malaysia, Angola etc.
all these countries. Okay. In Venezuela
when Venezuela's share of China's oil
imports is about 3 to 5% only the past 5
years. Okay. But it's still a major I
mean the major uh place where you have
oil reserves. So that's uh Venezuela and
China. Now what about India? Does
Venezuela export oil to India? So in the
2010s okay 2010 to 2020 around that time
period roughly Venezuela provided about
10 to 12% of India's crude oil imports.
Okay. So Venezuela was a major oil
supplier for India. But then the
Americans imposed sanctions. They
tightened the sanctions and this trade
came to a complete halt around 2020.
Okay. Because of US sanctions and in
2024 2025 India kind of started
restarted importing a little bit of oil
from Venezuela after taking permission
from the United States but it was about
1 to 2% of crude oil imports. Okay. So
the US is has now essentially or it's in
the process of securing control over
Venezuela's oil resources. So this will
reduce American vulnerability to any
kind of oil uh energy disruptions in the
Gulf. Yeah. It'll provide a buffer to
the US in case there are supply shocks
if there's a confrontation with Iran or
whatever. Right. Uh so uh so that's the
deal and this obviously will lower the
economic cost of a confrontation with
Iran if Washington decides to go down
that road and this will make any kind of
military pressure against Iran more
economically manageable even politically
manageable. So this is a great um you
know you could say master stroke of the
US. This is going to reinforce now that
the US controls an additional 20% of the
world's oil resources. This will now
further reinforce the central role of
the United States dollar, the US dollar
in energy markets. This will help
preserve the petro dollar system that is
the backbone of the global financial
system and American financial power.
Right? So that is the deal. That's the
deal. right now as of now it's just been
a couple of hours few hours since this
entire thing happened. Now what about
the other nations like um uh Argentina
Paro asks what are the other nations
that are aligned with Maduro's
government? So which are the nations in
Latin America or in the Americas that
are aligned with Venezuela? One is if
you want to talk about the core allies,
the core ideological and political
allies there's two. One is Cuba and the
other is Nicaragua. Nicaragua is where
the US had conducted a regime change and
they had captured abducted whatever you
want to call it Manuel Noriega back in
the day. So first Cuba Cuba is the land
of Fidel Castro and then later his
brother Rahul Castro. So Cuba has
historically provided political support,
intelligence support, diplomatic
support, etc. to Venezuela. So Cuba has
repeatedly affirmed and publicly
affirmed full and complete support for
Venezuela and Nicolas Maduro. So that's
Cuba. What about Nicaragua? So Nicaragua
is ruled by Daniel Ortega. Okay, his
government and he's he's a longtime
actor in the region himself, decades. So
Daniel Ortega's government regularly
supports and consistently supports
Venezuela and Maduro. It rejects
American sanctions, western, European,
EU sanctions, etc. And uh it it votes
with Venezuela on various regional and
multilateral forums. And the West
regards Nicaragua as part of this
authoritarian anti-US gang with Cuba and
Venezuela. Okay, regional the regional
anti-American block. That's Cuba,
Venezuela, and Nicaragua. So that is
these two nations. Then you also have
some other allies like Bolivia and
Honduras. Uh and whenever you have left
of center governments in Mexico, in
Brazil, in Colombia, they have
maintained good relations with Venezuela
and Maduro. But uh they also have not
been very consistent entirely totally
consistent in their support of
Venezuela. Uh so uh some of them see the
2024 election victory of Maduro it was
disputed by western nations and some of
these nations did not um offer
unconditional endorsement of Maduro when
he won. So that is the situation that's
that's the deal that those are the
allies of Venezuela or Maduro um in
Latin America. So what's going to happen
to these countries? That's the question.
Is the US going to go and invade them
too? Well, you know what?
What's the point of invading Cuba? You
know what? Cuba has been sitting next
door to the US. I mean, just offshore
from Florida, if you open the map, and
the US never bothered to do a regime
change there, right? And they were able
to do a regime change in a couple of
hours in Venezuela. So, what's the deal?
Why did the US never go after Cuba?
Well, there's nothing of any real
importance in Cuba. The US already has a
base on Cuban territory, Guantanamo Bay,
right? And there's no oil or any such
precious valuable resource in Cuba. So
let Cuba exist and and let the you know,
so that's been the kind of uh uh
approach towards Cuba. And when it comes
to the other nations uh Bolivia and uh
Nicaragua, etc., once again, there's not
a lot that these nations have to offer
in in terms of resources, etc. So the US
will essentially so the US action in
Venezuela is going to serve as an
example for everybody else. If you cross
the line, this is what happens. If you
stand against us, this is what happens.
So the other nations will now have to be
pragmatic and practical and they will
not really oppose the US too much.
And anyway these small nations to what
extent can they actually
you know oppose the US in any meaningful
way apart from you know moral opposition
or verbal opposition. Is there any
actual action then that that that can
take that can hurt the US? Not really.
So the US essentially is now going to
ensure that it completely controls the
western hemisphere. If there are some
dissidents here and there those will be
managed.
Um and this will serve as a reminder to
all other nations in the region that
you've got to stand you know you know
got you've got to tow the line whatever
the US says needs to happen you can
voice some opposition and some dissent
here and there but your actions cannot
be in opposition to US interests
so that is the situation right now and
this is a evolving situation it happened
just a few hours ago 3 4 hours ago um so
we'll we'll keep a very close eye on
this and this is going to have global
repercussions. It is connected to other
conflicts in the world. It is connected
to Ukraine. It's connected to the West
Asia region. It's connected to Israel,
Gaza, um Iran. It's also connected to
Taiwan.
Everything is in interconnected. So like
I said, this the the capture essentially
of Venezuela gives the US a big buffer
against any any potential oil shocks,
energy shocks that could emanate from
West Asia if it tries to, you know, do a
regime change in Iran. Now, how does
Russia respond? How does China respond
beyond diplomatic protests, etc. We'll
wait and watch. Yeah, because Russia and
China are hard retaliators.
They have demonstrated that they are
willing that they are capable of
retaliating in a hard meaningful way and
they're willing to do that. Russia did
Ukraine, China has done all kinds of
other things. So let us wait and watch
and we shall revisit this uh in the same
live stream tomorrow in 24 hours time.
Okay. So that's about Venezuela. Very
important development and the US is
essentially taking over the Western
Hemisphere. It's putting the the the
chess pieces on the board. But it's
setting the chessboard in the right
order so that it can take further action
in other parts of the world. Okay.
Real Vladimir Putin says with the recent
attack on Putin's house, what's going to
happen? Is it to provoke Russia into
more decisive actions so that they can
portray Russia as an aggressor?
Well, you know this all this entire
matter of portraying Russia as an
aggressor. Russia started a war with
Ukraine special military operation. They
don't respect the sovereignty, integrity
of Ukraine, etc. I mean, Venezuela,
the US did exactly the same thing in
Venezuela. They disregarded
international law.
What the US has done is an blatant
violation of U of international law. You
don't attack a sovereign nation. You've
got to respect the nation's territorial
integrity and sovereignty. Doesn't
matter if the US does it. If Russia does
it, very bad. Very, very bad. No, no,
no, no. Bad boy. I mean what sort of
double standards is this? Well, if you
are the most powerful nation in the
world, you can have any kinds of double
standards. Doesn't matter. You you you
have earned the right to be
hypocritical. So, see, Russia has
already been portrayed as as an
aggressor, right? So, what happened is
that Mr. Putin was on a phone call with
Mr. Trump,
okay? uh from his residence in Nogarod
if I'm not mistaken and Trump made sure
that the phone call lasts a long time
and the American agencies etc etc they
knew that Mr. Putin is in his residence
in Novgoroth and they passed on that
information to the Ukrainians who
launched series of drone strikes on Mr.
Putin's residence. It was an
assassination attempt. Now the Western
media and commentators and analysts are
saying that this what's the where's the
proof of this? The Russians are making a
false claim to provoke further action.
That's what they're claiming. Yeah,
it is what it is. So, uh, Mr. Modi has
tweeted his very great concern about
what's happened. Even other countries
have tweeted, leaders of other countries
have put out similar statements. So
look, from my perspective, there's no
question that this this thing happened.
There are there are videos of of um hits
u drone hits on the Kremlin and and
other major Russian um you know, places
where Mr. Putin generally either works
or resides.
So the Ukrainians, Mr. Zalinski and his
and his team, they tried to assassinate
Mr. Putin. What's going to happen now is
the question. So Russia has first of all
given evidence
of this to the United States
and they have said that our retaliation,
our response will not be diplomatic, it
will be military.
Um so it looks like there's going to be
you know calculated
retaliation
to what the Ukrainians have done. It is
possible they may even go after Mr.
Zillinski. It is possible. Okay, I'm not
advocating that they should go after m
Mr. Zalinski, but I'm saying it's
possible given that Zalinski went after
Putin's life,
you know, now I suppose all kinds of
cards are on the table now. So, what
happens now? So, we'll have to see.
We'll have to wait and watch. There's
going to be retaliation from Moscow,
military retaliation. What specific
retaliation? We'll have to see. Yeah.
But this is a major grave provocation
from Ukraine with the help apparently of
the United States.
Yeah. On Moscow. I mean attempting an
assassination of Mr. Putin. Mr. Putin is
he too trusting of the west? Is he too
is he under the belief that the west is
gentlemanly?
I mean the men courts Mr. Putin actually
tried to make the Ming Minsk Accords
work. And after Madame Angela Merkel
retired, she
said this in an interview that the Minsk
Accords were simply a ploy
to delay, I mean to to to
buy time, a ploy to buy time so that we
can arm Ukraine.
And they were sure the west that a war
will happen. And they were pushing
Russia towards a war. They were crossing
red line after red line. So the west
knew that the war is going to happen.
Russia will eventually be forced to take
military action. And the Minsk accords
were a ploy to buy time by a few years
to delay the Russian military action so
that they can bolster Ukraine's military
um capabilities.
And Mr. Putin got played by that by the
Americans by the West. Mr. Putin got
played.
He was too trusting
and it's it's true.
Ideally, he should have launched the the
special military operation in 2014
itself
when it took Crimea. Now, he was on a
phone call with Mr. Trump and he was
perhaps under the assumption that Mr.
Trump is a gentleman
and we are actually conducting
negotiation negotiations on the phone
and when I am talking to the my my my
colleague in in the United States as
gentlemen we will not do anything
against each other while the disc while
the diplomatic negotiations are
happening but while this is happening
the Americans pass apparently
information that Mr. Putin is in so and
so location to the Ukrainian Ukrainians
and they try to assassinate Mr. Putin
I
yeah so Mr. Putin seems to be a very
trusting not a very trusting person but
yeah he's kind of trusted the west on a
few occasions and the west has exploited
that I suppose there's no more trust
left anymore so let's see how how uh
Russia responds
to the
attempted assassination of Mr. Putin.
I'm sure there's going to be a response
and it's going to be military. We'll
see.
Hy Penguin says, "Why did Russia choose
to play the slow war uh track tactic
strategy whatever against Ukraine? How
is it more beneficial for the Kremlin?"
Yes. So what we are seeing the past see
the special military operation was
launched
in February 2022.
And very rapidly Russian forces were on
the outskirts of of Kiev etc. But then
they withdrew and there were massive
very rapid territorial exchanges for a
while. Then Russia took over Luhans,
Donetsk etc. those regions you know the
Donbas region which is ethnically
Russian majority which was and the
people there were very badly treated you
know brutalized for several years by the
Ukrainians after 2014 and so on. And now
the scenario is that of a slow war, a
frozen conflict, a war of attrition, a
slow grind, call it whatever you want.
That's the situation. So Russia has
decided consciously clearly to change
its uh strategy to a slow war, a
nutritional war. Okay. And what is the
reason for this? That's a very good
question. So this essentially
is about weaponizing time. It's about
turning time into a weapon. How so? Is
the question. How so? See, Russia is a
massive
military industrial base. Massive
industrial bass military base
essentially unlimited territory which
means essentially unlimited resources
you know coil sorry coal, oil, gas,
petroleum,
um minerals, iron, ore, whatever you
want to sustain a war. Raw materials,
they have it. and they have the
industries to turn those raw materials
into finished products, weapons,
munitions, and so on. So if you adopt a
slow war strategy,
Ukraine is a smaller nation. Ukraine's
manpower is much smaller, Russia's
population is much larger, Ukraine's
economy is smaller, Russia's economy is
way larger, etc. So by weaponizing time,
by grinding the war out over a long
prolonged period of time, you it's going
to have the effect of exhausting
Ukraine's manpower, exhausting Ukraine's
economy, exhausting the the West's
political will because see Ukraine, if
it were fighting with its own resources,
it would have lasted a week or two. And
then what do you do? Where do the arms,
ammunition, funds, etc. come from? They
have to come from the west. So the west
has been financing this war against
Russia, Ukraine's war against Russia or
Russ, you know, Ukraine's defensive war
against Russia, whatever you want to
call it. Okay? Without Western support,
Ukraine would have fallen a long, long
time ago. So now the longer the war goes
on the more it exhausts western
resources man not manpower but economic
resources financial resources material
resources political will right so Mr.
Putin is banking on Russia's larger
population. It's bank he is banking on
Russia's wartime industry. It's military
industrial complex. um and he knows that
he his nation has the resources to
endure a long conflict that can
potentially if if required last years
even a decade or two right and Ukraine
has constraints that Russia doesn't have
manpower ammunition finances goodwill
from the west etc right so over the past
2 three years Russia has been relying on
positional warfare it's relying on the
use of heavy artillery It's relying on
methodical assaults along the front
lines. And Russia has been willing and
it's actually had a strategy of having
slow advances,
not rapid adv and deep advances, slow
shallow advances in exchange for what?
In exchange for lower risk, lower
operational risk. And Russia has also
been um um you know doing systematic
strikes on Ukrainian infrastructure.
what kind of infrastructure, energy
infrastructure, logistical
infrastructure, industry, etc. And the
objective is to erode Ukraine's ability
to sustain the war. And
what happens when all the when Ukraine's
ability is eroded, it has Ukraine has to
be resupplied from the west over and
over again over and over again. Right?
So this is a long-term protracted
conflict that we are witnessing now. And
this stretches out costs
across the EU, across the west, across
the western nations, across NATO, right?
Um it obviously is there are many
nations that are now tired of this war.
No one wants, no one is enthusiastic
about this war anymore. So this
strategy is increasing pressure on
Western unity. It's testing whether the
United States and the European allies of
Ukraine are willing to sustain large aid
packages and and how long they're
willing to sustain these s you know
consistently keep giving these aid
packages to Ukraine. And what about the
domestic support? People are tired in
these nations. People are tired of the
of of their their economies and their
taxpayer money financing this this war.
Right?
So that's the situation. That's the
situation. Essentially, Russia has made
a calculated bet that it can sustain
high defense spending long enough to
outlast Ukraine and the West.
Right? And see, Russia's economy is
doing okay. It's not doing badly. It's
doing better than European economies.
Russia has reoriented its economy
towards a war industry, war footing.
It's boosted its production of
munitions. Uh if it's boosted its
production of artillery shells, drones,
armored vehicles, and it's importing
materials from from its partners such as
Iran, North Korea, potentially even
China. I mean, Chinese components are
being increasingly found in Russian
munitions, etc. So, that is the
situation. Russia is willing to wait as
long as it takes
until the West loses patience and uh
seeks an end to the war on Russia's
terms. What are Russia's terms? The
demilitarization of Ukraine, the
denazification of Ukraine and a regime
change in Kiev and the partition of
Ukraine and along lines that will be
decided eventually. So that's deal. That
is the deal. That's why Russia has
chosen to play play the frozen conflict
or slow war strategy against Ukraine.
Very beneficial. Makes sense.
Shikhar Bishwa says if the US pressures
Pakistan to deploy troops in the Gaza
Strip, does this not fundamentally
contradict Israel's security interests
given Pakistan's military and domestic
ecosystem is widely sympathetic to
Hamas? I would assume manage an
overwhelmingly anti-Israel domestic
audience and if Israel Israeli strikes
kill Pakistani soldiers does Pakistan
prioritize obedience to Washington or
regime legitimacy at home is Pakistan
now caught in a strategic crossfire and
how do you see this dilemma
realistically playing out for Pakistan's
military and regional positioning and
real Putin says with the recent talk
about Pakistani soldiers in Gaza what's
the update in the relationship ship
between Isra and the Pakistan.
Okay. So, first of all, what is the
situation right now? Pakistan as we know
is is not anymore a newly minted US fac.
It's been a big US fasal since 2022, mid
roughly 2022 when Imran Khan was ousted
in Shabbaz Sharif was was placed in in
that seat of prime minister. Right. So,
what has Pakistan said about Gaza?
Pakistan has said that it is willing in
principle whatever it means to join
President Donald Trump's Gaza peace
plan. Okay. So the US has proposed that
a USbacked international stabilization
force will act as a peacekeeping mission
in Gaza. Okay. So Pakistan has said that
we are willing in principle to to
participate in this. I don't know what
in principle means but it essentially
means that we will do what we are told
by our boss the United States by
President Trump whatever he says we
shall do. So
in the near term I'm not sure when this
entire thing will will will eventuate
the this peacekeeping force in Gaza or
the international stabilization force
but Pakistan is very likely
to be one of the first nations to join
this peacekeeping mission. Okay. And
they have said that we will do this. Our
mandate, the Pakistanis have said, I
believe that our mandate is is is
limited to monitoring the ceasefire, to
protecting civilians and uh humanitarian
support. Yeah. Uh and they have said
that there should be no explicit
requirement to disarm Hamas
apparently. Well, it doesn't work
without disarming Hamas. That's the core
objective of Israel. you know the
complete disarmament of Hamas and the
expulsion of Hamas from Gaza. So I'm not
sure how it works but that is what
Pakistan has said. Now the situation is
what about Israel? Yeah. How do how how
does Aim Munir convince his
overwhelmingly anti-Israel domestic
audience that this is five and what if
Israeli strikes kill Pakistani soldiers?
Well, first of all,
the Pakistanis have provided such
service in the past also in West Asia.
Za Hak, the the former Pakistani
dictator, what did he do? He killed
Palestinians, didn't he? He led a
Pakistani
force in Jordan. Let's let's Google
this. Zia
Hak
Jordan civil war.
So what did he do there?
He played a significant role as a
brigadeier in the Jordanian civil war of
1970. Black September he was etc etc.
King Hussein of Jordan gave Zeia command
of the Jordanian army second Jordanian
army second division. Zia led troops in
battles, helped guide tanks, was
involved in planning and execution of
counter offensive against the PLO and
Palestinian fid was instrumental in
military operations etc. And uh they
ended up killing about 25,000
Palestinians, the Pakistanis.
Okay,
that's what Zulhak did.
So now it looks like Aimun may have to
play possibly some kind of a role.
Maybe not what Zia did but you know some
kind of peacekeeping etc role in the
region. Now how can he convince his his
domestic audience? Well, he will say
that you know what we are actually
serving the people of Gaza. We're going
to ensure that there is no violence
against the people of Gaza. We're going
to ensure that uh President Trump who is
this great divine character, the peace
plan that he has proposed is the best
plan in the world and we're going to
ensure that the peace plan is
implemented and there's no more
suffering for the people of Gaza and
there's no more killing of the people of
Gaza. That sort of thing you can say and
well the Pakistani public will will lap
it up most likely.
Once again the question again is what's
the relationship between Israel and
Pakistan? That's the that's the core
question you're asking here clearly.
Well, that's a good question. See,
the United States is Israel's number one
supporter. It has always consistently
offered
unconditional support to Israel. We know
that. Yes.
The US also has a vasal state in the
form of Pakistan. Pakistan is a vasal
state of the US. So, so that means that
Pakistan and Israel should kind of be on
the same page on the same side, right?
It does kind of mean that that they're
actually in some sense allies.
Yes, Pakistan doesn't officially
recognize Israel.
Pakistan says
verbally all kinds of nasty stuff about
Israel. But from
action perspective, from the perspective
of actions, not words, what does
Pakistan do that do that hurts Israel?
Essentially nothing, right? Of course,
Pakistani terrorist activities have
ended up targeting Israeli citizens. For
example, 2008 Mumbai, the Mumbai attacks
were carried out by Pakistani terrorists
and they specifically targeted Israeli
civilians. So yeah, that was one
instance where Pakistanis targeted
Israelis but on Indian territory. Apart
from that, there's no other instance I
can think of where Pakistan has gone
after Israeli interests.
U verbal support etc. that that carries
no weight in my book. So Pakistan and
Israel are going to find a way to get
along. Yeah. And if Israeli strikes kill
Pakistani soldiers but well that's a
hypothetical. If it happens they'll the
Pakistanis will find some way of of you
know of ensuring that it doesn't cause
too much damage uh from a public opinion
perspective at home. So Pakistan see
Pakistan doesn't serve Israel. Pakistan
serves Washington. Washington and Israel
are on the same page which means
Pakistan and Israel are also essentially
on the same page.
Okay. Miranka Shikha Shikar Biswar says,
"Does Israel's move towards recognizing
Somali land signal a calculated attempt
to secure leverage over the Red Sea
encounter Houthi movement disruptions?
or is there a broader strategic
realignment at play especially given
strong opposition from the US and major
European powers? Additionally, how does
Somali lands largely Islamic society
reconcile political support for Israel
in the current regional and ideological
climate? And Karth Kartik says, "Could
you provide some history and context
about Somali land and why Israel chose
to recognize it and why are all the
other major countries criticizing
this move Somali land? So first of all,
let's go to the map. We haven't opened
the map today. So let's do that. Where
is Somali land and is it in a
geographically interesting location?"
So let's Okay. So okay, we are here. We
know where India is. Now we go
westwards. In west of India, we have
along the horn of Africa a nation called
Somalia. The capital is Mugadishu.
If you go northwards, there is a city
called Haresa,
which is part of Somalia, but it's
actually the capital of Somali land, a
de facto nation. So, let us search for
Somali land.
And then Google will Google maps will
show us this region. As you can see this
shaded region which is a de facto
separate nation. It is not controlled by
the government in Bogadishuh the
Somalian government. I mean whatever
government exists it's a de facto
separate nation. So that's the
situation. Now as you can see it's it
sits this nation is located essentially
at the
at the mouth of the Red Sea between the
Gulf of Aen and the and the Red Sea. You
have this choke point extremely
important geographic geographic choke
point the straight of Bab al-Mandde
okay
and Djibouti is the nation that uh over
kind of is is the nation at the choke
point apart the other one is Yemen south
Yemen and then we have Somali land
and of course you have Eritria also over
here Asara Eritria is kind of aligned
with the west so Djibouti is also you
could say aligned with the west and if
Somali land becomes aligned with the
west then they can control the entire
region through the use of these
territories and if they can create a
separate nation called south Yemen for
example which is controlled by the west
or by western allies in the region well
then the entire choke point is
completely controlled and you can choke
off at in on demand you know supplies
going eastwards towards China if you can
do the same thing if the West can for
example take over overthrow the Iranian
regime the government in Thran and uh
you know bring the blessings of
democracy and human rights to Iran then
they can also control the strait of
Hormuz
and by doing that they can they can
blockade
China see we in India talk about
blockading the straight of Malaka the
Americans don't worry about Malaka they
will blockade Bab al- mandib over here
and they will blockade hormones in in
case they are able to overthrow the
government in Thran and install a puppet
regime.
If they can do that, they can seriously
squeeze China without ever having to go
near Malaa.
That's how the US thinks. India thinks
of Mala. The US thinks of Babal Mand and
Hormuz and other things as well. So now
that we understand that Somali land sits
in a very interesting geographical and
geopolitically sensitive region location
that's the first thing we have to
understand. Now let's talk about the
history of Somali land. Okay. So the
capital capital of Somali land like I
said is Haresa that city in the north.
Somali land what is it and how how is it
a separate de facto country? So Somali
land is a self-governing breakaway
region in that region uh northwest of
Somalia like we saw on the map. It
operates as a de facto independent state
and until very recently it had no formal
international recognition. It's not a UN
member state for example. Yeah. So
Somali land has its own constitution. It
has an elected president. It has a
parliament. It has a government. It has
a judiciary. It has an army. Security
forces.
They have their own currency the Somali
land shilling and they hold separate
elections from Somalia. I'm not sure if
there are elections in Somalia but
Somali land has elections. Okay. So it
functions separately from Somalia from a
political perspective and administrative
p perspective. Somali land has not been
governed from Mogadishu since 1991. They
run their own domestic affairs. They
don't run their own external affairs. So
this is a classic de facto state. Now
how did this happen is the question. As
always we have to go back go back a few
decades and understand the history. And
when we talk about history we talk we're
going to talk about European
colonization. All these issues all these
problems the root cause goes back to
European colonization.
So from the late 19th century until 1960
this place called Somali land was ruled
by Britain. The British called it a
protectorate whatever it means. Okay.
And they ruled the place. It was called
British Somali land. Further south the
Italians ruled a place called Italian
Somali land which is today's Somalia.
Okay. To the south. So in the north you
had British Somali land. In the south
you had Italian Somali land. These were
two separate colonial territories with
different administration and different
administration styles and legacies and
so on. Okay. So 1960 I said right. So
1960 British Somali land became
independent. It became the state of
Somali land. It was recognized by more
than 30 nations. Okay. Including
permanent members of the UN security
council. But this situation lasted only
a few days. The same year the southern
state of Somali land it uh became
independent and the northern state of
Somali land voluntarily united with the
former
Italian ruled territory which had just
gained independence. So this formed
Somalia or the Somali republic and the
capital was in Mugadishu down south.
Then in the 1960s and 70s you had uh you
know you you the people of northern
Somali land okay they started getting
the sense that they were being
marginalized by Mogadishu okay um the
political and economic center of gravity
center of gravity is actually a term
yeah that was in in Moadeshu in the
south and it was the southern elites who
were ruling everything and the
northerners were marginalized. Then in
1969 there was a coup in Mogadeshu. It
brought it brought to power a gentleman
fine gentleman gentleman named Siad
Baret. Siad Baret. Let's let's see what
this fine gentleman looked like. Shall
we? Siad Baret.
So he was a dictator.
Siad Muhammad Siad Bar. He was a
military officer obviously and he was
the president of Somalia from 69 all the
way until uh 1991
right so Siad B comes to power Syad Bare
comes to power in Mogadeshu and he is
obviously a dictator authoritarian rule
and his treatment of northern the
northern part of Somalia which is Somali
land it obviously deepened the
grievances that the people of the region
had um and he he repressed them etc. His
policies were very nasty, brutal,
whatever you want to say. So then this
launched a movement to bring
independence to Somaland in the 1980s,
early 1980s. So an armed rebellion was
launched against the regime of Siad
Bareet and Siad Bareet's military forces
devastated uh the northern cities.
bombardment and you know all kinds of
human rights uh things and you know
standard standard atrocities that you
have in these in these in these
countries and so on. So large numbers of
civilians were killed. Many people had
to run away, flee into exile, you know,
and this essentially
this experience that the people of the
northern region had at the hands of Siad
Bar and his military regime that is
central to to the justification of
Somali land that it it that the union
with the south was intolerable and it
had to go. So in 1991, Siad Bar's regime
collapsed. Okay? And the central Somali
state down south ruled from the south in
Mogadeshu. It disintegrated.
There was no government anymore. Okay?
You had different different factions in
different regions, different warlords
and different pirates and god knows
what. Um I think there was a person
called Muhammad Farahid who was ruling
Mogadeshu and he was well he fought the
US for a while. Clinton was the
president. Yeah, that sort of thing. So
you had different factions in different
regions who asserted control and the
north came under the influence of the
Somali land independence movement
people.
So in 1991
um the people of northern Somal the
northern region Somali land they
declared independence. They said that
the 1960 union had effectively ended and
they proclaimed that the republic of
Somali land was now in existence within
the borders of the former British
occupied territory, the British
protectorate of British Somali land. So
they said that this was not a secession
from Somalia but a restoration of
independence. Okay, we had voluntarily
merged with Somalia but we were treated
brutally. We were oppressed and now we
are withdrawing and we are uh restoring
the independence that was rightfully
ours. Yeah. So that union was failed. It
was unlawful. It was oppressive and we
are we have exited from it. So that was
in 1991.
Right. Um and then they formed a
constitution I think in 2001. Uh they
drafted a constitution. There was a
referendum which adopted the
constitution. Um and Somali land was so
Somali land was was reconfirmed that it
was independent and its political system
um was was uh enshrined in the
constitution like we in India like to
say a presidential system a legislator
with an upper house and a lower house.
The lower house was a house of
representatives that was that would be
elected. The upper house would be an
unelected house of elders like an Indian
Raja Sabha kind of thing. Yeah. and
there was a limit of three political
parties to ensure that there is not too
much fragmentation in the country and
all that.
So that is how Somali land was formed.
It became separate from Somalia de facto
separate. So there is something called
the Monte Vidyo criteria. Okay. A
nation,
a sovereign nation has a defined
territory. It has its own population. It
has its own government. it has its own
capability to to to run its own economy
and international relations and so on so
forth. So Somali land it it satisfies
all the so-called Monte Vidya criteria
and yet it has remained largely
unrecognized from by other nations. Uh
the African Union doesn't recognize
Somali land. Many other nations don't
recognize Somali land. So what is the
reason for that? The African Union fears
that if we recognize Somali land, it
will encourage other secessionist
movements in the region in Africa and it
will undermine Africa's norm of
respecting colonial borders. So Africa
has this norm
that we will respect colonial borders. I
don't know why they have this norm.
They should disrespect in my opinion all
colonial borders. But Africa has a norm.
That's called colonization, mental
colonization. So Africa has the norm of
respecting colonial borders. And if if
we recognize Somali land, then it will
encourage other secessionist movements
and so on so forth and it will undermine
the norm of respecting colon borders. In
actually in the case of Somali land,
you're actually respecting the old coron
borders. But whatever
um that sort of thing and and Somalia
opposes the partition, right?
uh and then there are various nations
especially western nations that engage
with Somali land to
leo offices or whatever they call the
technical cooperation but they don't
recognize the country for example the US
the US has intermittently used the
Somali land territory for
counterterrorism operations
counterterrorism cooperation maritime
security arrangements in the Gulf of
Adan etc. But they don't recognize
Somali land. Ethiopia is a long-term you
know ally of Somali land. Now let's once
again revisit the map to understand why.
Okay where is map? We bring map. Let's
understand why Ethiopia is an ally you
could say of Somali land. So zoom in.
So there was a time when the the country
of Itria was part of Ethiopia but then
they broke free and they formed a
separate country and that had the effect
of landlocking Ethiopia. Ethiopia become
became a landlocked country. They don't
have access to the Indian Ocean. They
don't have access to the Gulf of Aen.
They don't have access to the Red Sea.
Terrible.
So that is the situation that was
imposed upon Ethiopia. So what did
Ethiopia do to let's say remedy this
situation? What Ethiopia did is that it
cultivated close economic and security
ties with Somali land and Ethiopia
has been for a long time using Somali
land's Burba port as an outlet to the
sea. Ethiopia needs access to the sea.
So they're using the Barbera port of
Somali land uh as this port of access to
the sea and uh in 2024 Ethiopia and
Somaliand signed a memorandum of
understanding that would give Ethiopia
access to a naval facility near Barbera
and the promise was that we will give
you give recognition official
recognition to Somali land and this
caused a crisis diplomatic crisis
between Ethiopia and Somalia that sort
of thing. The UAE is also um involved in
Somali land. They have secured a deal to
operate Barbara port, develop and
operate the Burbar port uh through a UAE
based company and they potentially may
build a military facility or air base
over there. So the UAE is involved in
Somalia's Somali lands uh economic
infrastructure and also security
infrastructure.
Saudi Arabia is also involved in various
ways you know religious economic
cooperation, security channels, um
livestock trade, countering extremism
etc. So Saudi Arabia is also aligning
its Somali land into its Horn of Africa
uh you know foreign policy and the
objective is to counter Iranian
influence and so on so forth. Now with
all that understood, all of that
understood. Okay, that's the history.
That's the history. Now a week or so
ago, Israel became the first nation to
formally recognize the Republic of
Somaliand as an independent and
sovereign country and they signed a
joint declaration of uh mutual
recognition with the president of
Somaliand. Mutual recognition means
Israel recognizes Somali land and Somali
land recognizes Israel. Right? And now
there there is
there is news that maybe India may or
may be on the way maybe on the way of
towards recognizing Somali land
potentially. Potentially yeah that sort
of thing. So that is the situation.
Okay that's the situation. Um so why has
Israel chosen to recognize it? Because
of the incredibly valuable important
geographical position location. Right.
Israel has faced a lot of problems from
the uh the Ansarah faction in Yemen, the
so-called Houthis and
the West wants to control the strait of
Bab al- Mand. So you you you control
Somali land, you control Djibouti, you
control itria,
that gives you one half of the of the uh
you know puzzle. And if you can create a
separate nation in Yemen, maybe South
Yemen or something that is aligned with
the west, then that is a done deal then.
So slowly but steadily all the pieces on
the chessboard are falling into place.
So that's why Israel has done this. It's
important for Israel that they are able
to control this region and that's
important for the US as well.
Right.
Aayush Singh says you mentioned that the
US in future will be moving towards
hemispheric defense but there is no sign
of US withdrawal from Asia in fact it's
making its presence even stronger than
before example recent 11 billion weapons
sales to Taiwan etc what's my opinion
okay so the US a few months ago came out
with this new national security strategy
right and once again let me repeat it
involves the Monro doctrine and the
Trump corollery
What is the Mandro doctrine be so that
we understand what we're talking about?
The Mandro doctrine was a policy, US
foreign policy from 1823. It said that
the Americas were closed to any further
European colonization or any other
interference. Any European inter
interference in the Western Hemisphere
in the Americas would henceforth be
treated as a hostile act against the
United States. So the US let let down a
red line that no external interference
will now be allowed in the western
hemisphere and they enforce it
eventually through military force
military strength. So that's the Monroe
doctrine. Now the national security
strategy 2025 talks about the Trump
corollery to the Monro doctrine. So it's
a contemporary modern 21st century
reinterpretation. It extends the idea of
the Monro doctrine. It says that the US
now has the right, it's going to assert
the right to be the super cop, the
policeman in the Western Hemisphere. The
US will police the Western Hemisphere.
It's going to police the Western
Hemisphere against extra regional powers
like China, Russia, whoever else wants
to influence the region. No longer
allowed. You all get out. Right? And it
will also police the region against u
regional actors such as uh you know drug
cartels etc. And the objective is to
preserve US dominance and and in the
region and to preserve security in the
region. So this is an imperial policy.
The US is now acting as a classical
empire. This is our domain. You're all
our vasals and we're going to police you
all. You you guys better not,
you know, get out of line and nobody
else from outside is allowed to, you
know, have any any influence or any
interference in the region. So that's
the national security strategy. So the
national security strategy it does
explicitly reenter
American strategy on the western
hemisphere. Okay. It says that American
pre preeeminence, American dominance,
American hedgemony in the western
hemisphere is a basic condition, a
central condition for America's national
security and prosperity. Okay, it says
that. So it revives the Monro doctrine.
It it adds the Trump corery to it. It
says that the US will will assert and
enforce its hedgemony in the region in
so many in whatever words it uses. Yeah,
it's my words I'm using but it has the
same meaning. It's going to deny
external powers which means non-western
hemisphere powers any strategic foothold
or military foothold in the region.
Okay. And this national security
strategy says that the US needs to
readjust its global military posture
away from regions whose relevance may
have declined for US uh you know for US
interests and the US will now reorient
its posture towards its missions in the
western hemisphere.
Okay. So what are the elements of this?
First of all, Europe is being
downgraded. America's ties with Europe
are being downgraded. Europe is now
expected to shoulder much more of the
financial burden of its security. See
the US is part of NATO. It is the
hegemonic power in in NATO and the other
nations are all in apart from Canada are
all in Western Europe. Yeah. Mostly and
the US has been financing NATO for the
for the most part all these years. And
now the US requires that European
nations must double their expenditure
towards NATO from 2.5% to to 5% by about
2030 around around that time. Um so the
Europeans are now expected to put much
more shoulder much more of the burden of
NATO right so Europe is being
downgraded. Um and not just Europe it's
EMA there's this region called EMA in in
business in business pagnos EMA means
Europe Middle East and Africa. Okay. So
this entire region Europe, Middle East
Africa ENA is being downgraded and uh
the US is now going to focus on
hemispheric defense. It's going to
prioritize its hemispheric defense over
its global forward presence.
Now please understand that it is not
just black and white. It sounds like the
US is completely retreating but it is
not. the US the national security
strategy document it still treats China
and Russia as major adversaries okay and
it is linking the the hemispheric
security to global great power
competition so the strategy doesn't say
that we need to give up all our tools
for projecting power outside of the
western hemisphere it doesn't say that
we need to shut down all our extr
territorial military bases the US has
more than seven or 800 extr territorial
military bases beyond its territory many
of them are in the eastern hemisphere,
right?
130 roughly of them are in Japan. More
than 100 are in South Korea. Is the US
going to shut shut that down? Absolutely
not. Okay. So, the the the US strategy
is going to continue to maintain those
tools for projecting power in the
eastern hemisphere. Okay? And u and
they're going to be open to using
military force wherever required. So the
policy is hemisphere first, not
hemisphere only. They're going to
prioritize the western hemisphere, but
they're not withdrawing as such from the
eastern hemisphere. They want to reduce
the potential of of overstretching
themselves, right? And they want to
preserve their capacity to compete
globally from a stronger position in the
Western Hemisphere. That is the deal. So
the US is not giving up on its global
influence. It's not giving up on the
alliances and vasal vasal,
you know, arrangements it has across the
world. It's not giving up any of that.
It's not giving up any of its power
projection capabilities. It's reordering
the way it approaches the problems it
faces in the world. It's not abolishing
any of the rules it currently plays.
So
its position in the western hemisphere
is now going to be you could say a
neoimperial posture. They can see the
effect of that right away. A few hours
ago they took over Venezuela,
right? It's going to be a muscular
approach in the western hemisphere and
outside it's going to shift the burden
to its vasals. So the vasals will will
shoulder more of the burden and the US
will lose none of its power projection
capabilities. So that is the situation
right it's it's more nuanced than simply
withdrawing into the western hemisphere
and hemispheric defense
realm Putin says what's your opinion on
the Chinese foreign minister Wang Yi
claiming that China mediated between
India and Pakistan in the in the 3D war
well China thinks that you know what
Trump has been claiming that they have
mediated that they have ended the war so
why not we also make some claims
what's my opinion my opinion is that we
don't need to take it seriously.
Yeah, we don't have to take it
seriously. The Chinese were aiding
Pakistan in real time, supplying
Pakistan with real-time information,
intelligence, satellite imagery and
whatn not during the three-day war,
operation sindur, right? So, while they
are actively
aiding Pakistan, you think will they'll
be in a position to come and mediate?
When you take sides, you can't mediate,
right? You can't. So this Pakistan this
Chinese claim is a joke and we should
treat it as a joke. We we should not
take it seriously. It's yeah funny kind
of
Aayush Singh says we are hearing
constant conversations of a nuclear
Japan which was unheard of since the
second world war. Henry Kissinger had
predicted this years ago and there's a
video of mine on this topic now that
things are evolving at such a rapid
pace. could you please tell the story of
it effects it will have power balance in
East Asia will that change and so on
so um a while ago few months ago I had
put out this tweet let's put that on the
screen
okay and this is a quote by Shri Henry
Kissinger G that Japan is heading
towards becoming a nuclear power in 5
years he said this in 2023 and 2023 is
the year that he tragically passed away
at the age of 00 he was a great global
statesman and uh he no no no one
understood global diplomacy and
geostrategy etc. U very few people
understood it the way he did because he
was part of it for so many decades. So
he said in 2023 that Japan is heading
towards becoming a nuclear weapons power
in 5 years. So that gives us the end
state in 2028. So according to what he
says, what he what he said, Japan, if
things go as per his prediction, Japan
should become a nuclear weapon state by
2028. This is 2026. Today is January 3,
2026. We've got 3 years. 26, 27, 28. In
3 years, will Japan become a nuclear
weapons state? So I spoke about the US
national security strategy. It is now
focusing primarily on the Western
Hemisphere. It's consolidating its new
imperial muscular
stature, a muscular policy in the
western hemisphere and in the eastern
hemisphere. It is forcing its vassals to
shoulder much of the economic and
military burden of
which of of of their defense military
defense and of uh supporting American
bases and American power production
capabilities. That's what the US is
doing. Now when it comes to
the far east, Japan, South Korea, Japan
and South Korea are two major American
vessels. These two nations have been
under permanent US milit military
occupation for decades. Japan since
1945, Korea, South Korea since the 1950s
now.
Does it make sense for the US allowing
Japan
to acquire nuclear weapons?
Well, things are changing very rapidly
this year. Let's say Venez see Venezuela
has fallen. Venezuela is now the
property of the US. Hypothetically, if
sometime later this year or the next two
years the Americans take out Iran,
then China will well there'll be a
tremendous amount of pressure on China
because Iran is one nation from which
China acquires a lot of uh oil energy
and if the US controls that well well
and China has a 25-y year strategic
agreement with Iran. So China loses a
major ally if if Iran goes in that case
China will be very tempted to go after
Taiwan. Maybe Taiwan may happen
irrespective of that. So in that case it
makes sense for Japan to be way more
powerful than it is right now but still
under US control.
So
you know that from that perspective it
may it may make sense for the Americans
to allow Japan to become a controlled
nuclear power in such a way that you
position nuclear weapons on Japanese
soil but you retain the control. The big
red button is in Washington not in
Tokyo. That sort of nuclear weapons
power. So essentially American nukes on
Japanese soil which you could say makes
Japan well a place where you have
nuclear weapons if not a nuclear weapons
power that may be very tempting for the
US right especially if China becomes
desperate or whatever and they you know
do some saber rattling make some moves
so it will significantly change the
balance of power in East Asia for sure.
See right now China has to worry about
India
because of its own actions. India has no
desire to be the enemy of China an
adversary of China. It is China that is
acting in an adversarial fashion which
is why India has had to take various
measures to ensure its national
security. One of the measures is a
nuclear triad
land based airbased and sea based
nuclear offensive nuclear capability.
Right? We have nuclear submarines. We
have ballistic missiles. We have air
based uh you know uh nucle a nuclear
detent that's air based and groundbased
as well.
And we have a reasonably good quantity
of nuclear warheads. So all of that is
to ensure that you know China doesn't
China doesn't do anything stupid.
So now so China has that to worry about.
Now if Japan also becomes a nuclear
power then it then China has to worry
about two nuclear weapons powers.
Pakistan but Pakistan can also
potentially be used against China
because Pakistan is controlled by the
US. So you see the the headaches that
that China faces could multiply rapidly.
If you bring South Korea again into the
picture and station nuclear weapons
there as well. Well, China gets
encircled and it's not like China is on
very friendly terms with Russia. China
treats Russia as a junior partner. So
making Japan a nuclear weapons power
will significantly alter the balance of
power in East Asia and uh yeah it it
does make sense from a strategic
perspective. So we'll see if Mr. Ker was
right or not. There were three years in
which in which we can either prove or
disprove his his claim his uh his
prediction. Let's say
real brother Putin says two nations Iran
and India. Iran is facing a lot of
sanctions in Iran is a much smaller
economy than India much more inferior
military hard power than India. Yet it
funds a lot of proxies in the Middle
East. India being such a much larger
economy being the fourth most strong
strongest military power doesn't do any
of that. Why?
Why? See, Iran
is nowhere compared to India on the hard
power scale. Nowhere. Yeah.
Um, Iran doesn't have nuclear weapons.
Iran is a small economy. Iran is a small
conventional military compared to India.
And yet, Iran projects power across West
Asia. Let's go to the map. Uh, give me a
second. Let me bring the map on the
screen. Okay. Iran projects power in in
in large regions of West Asia. See,
Iran projects power in Iraq. Iraq at
least 50% of Iraq's population is Shia
Muslim and Iran is a Shia Muslim nation.
So, Iran is able to project power in
Iraq. Uh until last year, Iran had an
ally in Syria. Now, you have an al-Qaeda
government in Syria. So, that's over.
Iran has
has friends in Lebanon. You know, Iran
is able to project power in Lebanon as
well. And Iran is able to project power
in Yemen as well because its ally is the
Ansarah faction, the Houthis.
So Iran has plenty of power projection
capabilities in the region. Iran also,
let's not forget, has an ally in
Armenia. Iran is an ally of Armenia. A
Shia Muslim nation is an ally of a
Christian nation in the Caucasus region
and the other ally is a Hindu nation
India. Very interesting scenario over
there. So Iran despite being much weaker
than India projects so much power
in West Asia, right? It has it's able to
fund proxies. it's able to have those
proxies work on its behalf and and you
know uh
geopolitically, geostrategically
and so on. So that's why when people
talk about the powerful nations they
talk about the US, China, Russia, Iran,
North Korea, no one talks about India.
India historically has been a soft
state, a punching bag. Pakistan keeps
punching, jabbing, jabbing, jabbing,
jabbing. India just keeps absorbing it.
Doesn't even fight back. Doesn't even
defend itself. Right? That was the situ
situation until until 2014. Now it's
kind of different but we still are that
kind of nation where we are funding
proxies across the board
and having them fight on our behalf.
One reason is that Iran is an Islamic
nation in an Islamic neighborhood. And
whenever wherever in West Asia in
whichever nation or whichever region you
have Shia Muslim populations there's
going to be an affinity between them and
Iran and Iran is able to weaponize that.
So Iran has never been a punching bag.
Iran has never been a soft set. It's
been a very hard state. It kind of
punches above its stature. It punches
up. India historically hasn't punched at
all except once or twice and then sit
down again. Iran also has the advantage
of political continuity, political
stability. Since 1979, the same
government, right? So, there's long-term
execution of policies and that's why
they have been able to cultivate things
long-term.
And Iran is a geopolitically ambitious
nation. Iran regards itself as the
leader of the Islamic world.
Iran doesn't regard itself as a nation
who will follow someone. We will lead.
We were once a great empire. We are an
ancient nation. Who are you all to talk
to us? We should lead you. We will lead
you. So that's the attitude Iran has.
India is the most ancient civilization
of all. But the Indian government is a
colonial government. The entire
structure is colonial. India is defined
as a as a secular nation. India's
official policy dis dissociates itself
from our civilizational status.
the Indian government and Indian the
Indian machinery regards India as a
nation state not as a civilization state
and that's why and in India we have
democracy which means every 5 years at
least you're going to have potential
change of government and you've had lots
of changes of government in the past
before 2014 you had coalition
governments where they where where
there's a coalition government there's
essentially nothing happens
and governments come and war come and go
come and go that sort of so there's
political stability, there's no
continuity of of of of policies and so
on. That's why India has never had a
long-term proper policy. It's only right
now the past since 2014 that we have had
the same prime minister that we've had a
focus and and a clear direction and
clear focus on what our policy should
be.
And yet India
and so if you want to have proxies who
operate for you, you have to cultivate
them for a long time. You can't
cultivate proxies around the world in 3
years
even 10 years takes time
and see India doesn't have the
advantages that Iran has even if it is
now geopolitically ambitious
it even if it may now be geopolitically
ambitious we don't have the advantages
the Iranians have which is the which is
all the Shia populations in West Asia
right who are often oppressed
by the other populations where they live
if they're minorities which which will
obviously make them easier to weaponize
by Iraq. We don't have any such thing.
We don't we have Hindu diasporas and all
but Hindus are not a political people,
right? Hinduism is not a political
religion and even if Hindus are
oppressed, the government doesn't care.
Um so it's a combination of various
factors, right?
So that's why India acts very
differently from Iran.
Nirvana Shank says Chanaka emphasized
pragmatism, strategy and moral
flexibility. How can his Art Shastra
principles be applied to India's modern
governance and foreign policy? Right?
So the shastra is a vast vast text. You
cannot boil it down or distillate it
down to like three principles. But yeah,
pragmatism, strategy, moral flexibility,
flexibility, all these are uh you know
principles that Chanaka did write about.
Now when it comes to this one here,
moral flexibility, what do we mean by
that moral flexibility?
Does it mean that you can do anything,
any nasty thing and it's okay be morally
flexible? It doesn't mean that moral
flexibility. Moral flexibility means if
you have
a good long-term objective that is
genuinely good for your nation for and
for your people then to achieve that
good objective it is okay to sometimes
be morally flexible. Let's say your
objective is the long-term security and
prosperity and national integrity and
integrity
of the nation and its people. That is a
worthwhile objective to have. So in the
pursuit of that objective, you can
sometimes be morally flexible. That's
what Vishnutaka said. You may sometimes
war wage an unjust war potentially
against somebody.
Okay? See, if if you are the king, you
only serve your people. You don't serve
the people of the rest of the world. So,
your only job is to serve your people
and do everything that is in their
interest. If you can achieve their
interest at the expense of somebody
else's interests, then it's okay. That's
what Vishna Gupta Chanaki said. That's
called moral flexibility.
So, these principles are applied in real
in the real world, not by us, but by
everybody else. Pakistan is better has
historically been better than India
at le using China principles. What the
US does is pure Chanakin real politic
isn't it? Purely
their policy is completely amoral. I'm
not saying immoral. I'm saying amoral.
That's what the US policy is. I mean
today they have taken they they took out
Maduro in Venezuela today a couple of
hours ago 4 hours ago
they are doing and is it good for
Venezuela they're going to essentially
turn Venezuela into Wasal state and the
only real real reason why they want
Venezuela is because it's home to 20% of
the world's proven oil reserves that's
it it's a golden goose what happens to
it people etc who cares
what about human rights freedom
democracy who cares so that's what the
US does so all these principles, India
can also
use them
in the pursuits of its own national
interests. When it comes to let's say
domestic politics in India, don't you
see moral flexibility all the time?
Don't you see the same set of principles
being applied in domestic politics in
state level politics, district level
politics, national level politics?
Don't various political parties
routinely absorb
individuals who who are members of other
political parties, but just because I
want your constituents in your votes,
I'll I'll make you a member of my party.
I'll even give you a cabinet position
potentially. Sometimes
you may have been a member of my
opposition party, but now that you are
part of my party, I'll give you some
perks and rewards as long as you deliver
the results I want. That's called moral
flexibility. What happened to the
party's ideology? Well, we're going to
make sure that they will become part of
our ideology and they'll adhere to our
ideology. And we are doing all this
maybe it may sound little not not very
nice but we are doing this for the right
reasons. So that's the justification
that certain political parties or
politicians will give and if they are
doing the right thing for the right
these things for the right reasons well
maybe it makes sense. So and when it
comes to governance
well we can learn a lot about taxation
etc from the ashastra the right way to
do taxation
I mean just one tax should be enough we
don't need all these different tax labs
and blah blah blah blah blah
taxation upon taxation upon taxation you
already paid income tax now with the
little money that's left after paying
income tax on top of that from that
money you have to pay to pay road tax
and this tax and that tax and GST and
what not. I mean, why just have one
single tax on everybody? Make it as
simple as possible.
Don't overburden people with taxes.
Don't underburden them either. The
government runs on taxation. So,
taxation is legitimate. Everybody will
pay. But make it simple.
It looks like the tax tax uh department
a lot of it exists just as an employment
generation scheme to keep people
employed. Why do we need that? So
there's a lot we can learn from the from
the Ara shastra to keep things simple
about law and order about geopolitics
about geostrategy about engaging with
allies and adversaries about power
projection so many things and the other
nations they do it they do what
Vishnuaneka said wrote about we are kind
of catching up now
Mishna says it's often said that we are
living in the most difficult times today
with geopolitical instability economic
inequality, climate change, social
unrest. But compared to some of the most
devastating periods in human history,
536 to 540 AD, the volcanic winter and
plague of Justinian 1347 to 1351, the
black death in Europe, 1939 to 1945, the
Second World War. Compared to these
periods, we can truly consider, can we
truly consider today the worst era? Why
or why not? We are actually living in a
very good era. There are some parts of
the world where people are obviously
facing terrible uh circumstances. A lot
of Africa is like that. See when we
discuss the world, we kind of disregard
Africa, right?
But Africa is part of the world. But
overall, if you look at Eurasia, if you
look at the Americas, North and South
America, if you look at Oceanania,
Australia, etc. If you look at China,
Russia, Japan, all these countries,
there's relative prosperity everywhere.
There's no major war that's happening.
Ukraine is is a like we discussed a
frozen conflict. Apart from Ukraine,
apart from the situation in Sudan, etc.
in Africa, it's always Yeah.
But apart from that, there's no major
devastating disaster that's happening
right now. There's been no major
devastating war since 1945. Okay, Korea
happened, sure. Iran, Iraq happened,
sure. But these were localized
conflicts.
The four India Pakistan wars happened.
Again, localized conflicts. India,
China, again, no localized conflicts. A
conflict.
There's been no major devastation.
There's been no major pandemic since
1918. I mean, well, we had one recently
which was kind of not nice to put it
mildly, but it not did not have any kind
of anything near the effect that you had
in the 1918 Spanish flu pandemic.
Corona virus was nothing like that.
Mortality rate was much lower, death
toll was much lower and so on.
So overall, you had many periods of time
in the world where things were way, way,
way worse than what we have today.
Of course, there's geopolitical
instability. That's always part of the
menu. Right now, it's more than usual,
but it is what it is. Economic
inequality. There's always economic
inequality.
Inequality is a feature of the universe.
It's a feature. It's a permanent feature
of existence. Inequality.
Every nation, no matter how prosperous,
is going to have inequality. But what
you need
is social mobility,
which means that okay, it's it's an
unequal world. Can't do a thing about
that. But let's say someone's poor,
they should have the means
to become prosperous. If you're poor,
you should not be condemned to poverty
for the rest of your life. If the
society that you live in gives you the
means and the avenues for bettering your
your standard status in life then it's a
fair society. Inequality is going to be
there. Yeah. So inequality what's the
big deal? I mean it's always been there.
Climate change the climate has always
changed. There's always been climate
change. Social unrest I can show you
times periods of time when you had
tremendous social unrest.
nothing I mean way more compared to
today. So, you know, we are actually
living in one of the most prosperous
times,
prosperous periods of history in the
world. If you're living outside Africa,
if you're in Africa, well, I'm sorry to
say, yeah, things are bad there. Yeah.
But yeah,
in in the West especially when they
discuss the world, they don't talk about
Africa because of what they've done to
it. So anyway uh if you disregard the
situation in Africa much many parts of
Africa then overall things are good
and even in Africa things are kind of
better than in the 19th century when the
Europeans destroyed Africa devastated
Africa so it's not that bad in Africa
also so this is not the worst era I do
not consider this to be worst the worst
era by by a long stretch not at all
okay now we'll discuss discuss Some
history questions. Amisha says, "What is
the history behind the migration of
Indians to the Caribbean? Can it be
regarded as slavery?" Well, it was
called indentured labor. So, if you go
to the Caribbean region today, the West
Indies,
where is it? Let's go to the map, sir.
So the West Indies is
in the Atlantic Ocean. Okay.
Between North and South America in the
Caribbean Sea. All these islands here
are the West Indies, the Caribbean
region. You have Cuba. You have
Hispanola, which is in the Dominican
Republic. You have Puerto Rico over
here. And then you have Jamaica,
Kingston, Jamaica, Sabina Park. I'm sure
everyone who knows cricket knows that.
And then you have uh the British Virgin
Islands, Antigua and Barbuda, St. Kits,
Nevice, Monzerat, Guadalupe, Dominica,
Martineik, St. Lucia, St. Vincent and
the Grenadians, Barbados, Bridgetown,
Barbados.
Here we have Bridgetown Barbados. Then
you have Grenada, you have Trinidad and
Tobago over here, Port of Spain, very
famous place if you know cricket. And
then you have uh yes, so that's about
it. That's the Caribbean region. I'm
sure I've missed this Bermuda as well.
There's a Turks and Kikos Island. So
this is the Caribbean region. Now if you
Indians know about the Caribbean because
of cricket India plays cricket U versus
the West Indies which is a team that's
composed of multiple Caribbean nations
grouped together. And if you talk about
the West Indies, the West Indies cricket
team has always had multiple players of
Indian origin, right? Rohan Khai, Albin
Khalichan,
um
Ramdin
Sharan Chandapal,
uh Mahendra Dagabut, I'm sure I'm
missing a lot of names. Yeah, some of
the all-time greats from the West Indies
have been of Indian origin.
Ram Naresh Tarban. So why do we have so
many Indians in the West Indies?
And what about the island of Mauritius,
Il Moraice?
So if you go to Mauritius, it's in the
Indian Ocean. You go down south from
India and go westwards and east of
Madagascar, you have Borlui, that is
this is Mauritius and then you have Il
Reo which is a French island which also
has a substantial population but
Mauritius is Indian majority. So it's
it's technically part of Africa.
uh the local language is French or it is
Morish
and the majority population is Indian of
Indian origin the majority religion is
if I'm not mistaken Hinduism
um
yeah so you you have that you also have
lots of Indians in South Africa lots of
Indians there you go to Durban for
example significant Indian population in
Durban Durban over here next to Peter
Marittsburg Cape Town also So you have
Indians there, right? So Indian
populations in various parts of the
world, all colonial parts of the world.
How did this happen? How did Indians end
up over here? How did Indians migrate to
the Caribbean, South Africa, Mauritius
and so on.
So this was a system of what the British
called indentured labor. Indentured
labor under contract. It was created,
the system was created to replace slave
labor. Okay. So the British, you know,
the British Parliament, it passed the
slavery abolition act in 1833. The
British and by extension the white
people, Europeans, they like to claim
and proclaim on social media, we
abolished slavery. We abolished this
evil system. Right? They Elon Musk says
that all the time. We abolish slavery.
But the slavery that they abolished, who
started it, who institutionalized
slavery
that the British ended, they themselves
did that? The Americans had slavery. The
British used slaves. And then 1833, the
British end slavery. And that's why
they're the good guys apparently, right?
So in 1833 the British Parliament passed
this slavery abolition act and this
created a severe labor shortage on
various sugar plantations uh in various
parts of the world. Okay.
Uh so to to replace that they created
the system of indentured labor under
contract. U in practice this indentured
labor under contract it functioned as a
new system of slavery. It was highly
coercive but it was legally distinct
from slavery from chatt slavery. So
indentured servitude is different
legally from chatt slavery because in in
indentured servitude you have contracts
you have nominal wages you have time
limits and so on. But in the real world,
you had recruitment fraud. You had,
you know, physical punishment. You had
what they called plantation discipline.
You had lethal working standards.
Essentially, most workers had no real
freedom. They were essentially the same
as slaves. They were treated like
slaves. When you moved to a when you
were brought to a plantation, your life
was at the mercy of the white overlord.
Yeah. You had to do what you were told.
Yeah. So there was a very little real
freedom. So the British ended slavery
you know by passing this act and then
they launched what they called the great
experiment in indentured migration
and they decided that we will go looking
towards India for a large cheap
workforce. India Indians are plentiful
right? So we'll get labor from India. So
in the 1830s so 1833 the act is passed.
Next year the the the the English the
British started a movement of bringing
Indian laborers indentured laborers to
Mauritius. Okay to work on various
plantations in Maicius. Eventually by
between 1834 and 1920 about half a
million Indians were brought to
Mauritius as indentured laborers. Okay.
And most of them came from Bihar, Uttar
Pradesh and some of them came from
southern parts of India.
I've had friends from Mauritius
personally
mostly from they are mostly from Bihar,
Uttar Pradesh. Some are of Marathi
origin and some are of at least one of
my friends was of Tamil origin. Right?
So that's what was done
and these these uh laborers they had to
sign contracts multi-year contracts okay
they would work on sugar plantations
sugar estates sometimes they would be
redistributed like goods to some other
places maybe from one estate one
plantation to another one sometimes from
one colony to another col colony maybe
in the Indian Ocean maybe to the
Caribbean etc so initially it starts
with Mauritius okay 1834 all the way to
the 1920 to the to the 1920s. Okay. Then
this then they start sending Indians to
the Caribbean also. Okay. They started
shipping Indian workers to British
Guyana sometime in the 1830s.
Um and the government of British India
which is the British occupation
government of India the British
occupiers they enacted some legislation
in India which uh legalized the
transportation of Indian laborers to
places like Jamaica like Trididad to
places like Deara
if you have heard of Deara sugar that's
the place it it came from then in the
second half of the 19th century from
1850s all the way to the 1870s in almost
1900 um this became a systematic
practice. Take Indian laborers, make
them sign contracts, ship them off to
some part of the world. Okay. So
about
2 million Indians in total 20 lakh were
transported as de facto slaves to I
don't know 10 20 colonies Maicius
various islands in the Caribbean
Trinidad, British Guyana, Jamaica,
Suridam. Okay. also to Fiji, also to
Natal province in South Africa and also
to places like Malaysia, Malaya and East
Africa, also to Sri Lanka. Um,
Surinam
was ruled by the Dutch. They began
importing Indians
from the in the second half of the of
the 19th century uh through an agreement
with the British Empire. Okay. So the
British owned the goods and the Dutch
decided agreed with the British that we
will import your goods which is Indian
laborers and then you had Indian
laborers who started coming to Surinam
and started started working there. They
had five-year contracts. Okay. The
promise was that after your your
contract is over you'll be sent back
home. But that hardly ever happened. Um
so eventually this system of indentured
slavery, indentured servitude, it was
ended around the second decade of the
20th century by 19 roughly 1920 or
something. Um so but but whichever
contracts were signed they they ran into
the 1920s. So what happened is that you
know in India there was this severe see
India had been de-industrialized by the
British. India had been devastated by
the British. The British had engineered
hundreds of artificial famines in India.
Indians were starving. India's economy
was was being destroyed in real time.
There was because India was
de-industrialized. All the all the all
the jatis of of the various people that
we have in India, their traditional
occupations had been destroyed. So there
was no way to earn money and to sustain
families, right? So people needed
employment anyhow. So that's how they
were able to you know lure Indians into
signing contracts. The promises were
often that you'll get a high wage etc.
Maybe sometimes some people were even
kidnapped into doing this. Yeah. The
fact is that the wages were very low.
The wages could be withheld withheld
based on any any flimsy pretext. Okay.
Um whatever men earned women earned
maybe twothirds of that maybe 3/4s of
that. So women earned less than men and
if you deserted, if you did not work one
day or you you tried to run away, you
were treated as a criminal. Um, every
day you were given tasks, if you could
not finish your task, then you would be
severely penalized. Maybe you'll be
flogged, beaten, maybe your fine your
your your wages will be withheld. Maybe
they will find you three months wages or
whatever. Maybe you'll be imprisoned.
maybe you'll be killed.
Killing was was not that that frequent
because the labor was of course valuable
that sort of thing. And once the
contract of the indentured labors was or
laborers was over, they were supposed to
receive a free trip back to India or a
subsidized trip back to India.
But typically this never happened. Very
very few of few of them these people
were able to return to India. So even
eventually over time
these indentured laborers who were
essentially de facto slaves they just
settled down in the places where they
had been transported and they became
essentially the foundations the
foundations of the societies Indian
societies of Trinidad of Ghana of
Surinam of Mauritius PG and so many
others. They were able to preserve their
languages, whatever language they spoke.
They were able to preserve their
religion, Hinduism. They were able to
preserve their cultural practices and
they also created new local entities,
the Indian diaspora, right? Um,
so that was that's the story of the
indentured
Indians who were shipped off to far away
parts of the world.
Right. So it's it was essentially a new
system of slavery.
That's what it was. That's the story.
Okay. Um
next question. Nirvana Shanks says, "Was
the British Empire's real power its navy
or its bureaucracy?"
The British Empire and its real power
navy bureaucracy. Well, you see, it is
naval power, sea power
that made the British Empire possible.
Without sea power, the British Empire
would never have existed.
So, it all started with piracy. Uh,
Queen Elizabeth,
she was the patron of pirates. She
funded piracy in the Atlantic and
beyond. At that time, the British Navy
was not very capable. So, they relied on
guerrilla tactics. They had these
privateeers, pirates who would uh engage
in slave trade and whatn not and and and
theft and piracy. But eventually the
British navy get got better and it is
this naval power that made the British
Empire possible. So without the naval
power there was no British Empire. So
the naval power made the British Empire
possible but bureaucracy made it
durable, longived and governable. Right?
So
the British started acquiring
territories slowly in various parts of
the world. So the navy was the
foundation of this expansion of the
British footprint and eventual global
reach of Britain. And then they had to
administer the territories that they had
occupied. So the Portuguese were not
good at this. But the Brit British they
demonstrated they were really good at
this. So they had to create an
administrative machine, an imperial
administrative machine that would turn
the capture of a territory into
longlasting control and revenue through
extraction by various means. Right? So
the British Navy its job was to secure
the control of sea lanes and trade
routes. Its job was to protect merchant
shipping the ships that would be
transporting all the plundered resources
from India for example. Okay. So the
naval royal the British Royal Navy it
protected this merchant shipping. It
secured the control of the sea lanes and
through this it was able to it enabled
Britain to project its power globally.
So today you have the US that projects
power globally through its network of
extr territorial bases and the US Navy.
Well, the British did the exact same
thing. The British Navy did the exact
same thing during the British u empire.
So that's that's that was the rule of
the British Navy and the naval supremacy
of the British. It allowed the British
to blockade its their enemies. It gave
the British the power to prevent any
invasion of the British islands. Without
the home base, what do you do? And the
navy also supported campaigns that
captured territories like Canada, like
India. So the primary strategic asset of
the rise of the British Empire was the
British Navy. But once these territories
were acquired, the British used imperial
institutions, the civil services, the
Indian civil service for example.
These institutions, they converted
the territory and the raw power of the
British into systems of authority, of
governance, tax collection, law, etc.
Right?
And they over time the British developed
elaborate techniques, administrative
techniques like you know writing the
law, codifying the law for for for a for
a colony um civil services that are
based on merit and so on. So by doing
this this allowed a small number of
officials to manage huge populations in
huge territories for long periods of
time.
Uh so that's the situation. The
bureaucracy was very important. It was
very important for the British. The
naval power always came first. But the
bureaucracy became the the the main
instrument of ever everyday domination.
So when you have moments of military
success,
those moments of military success have
to be converted into long-term rule over
a territory. So the naval power did
that. it it at these moments of naval
success. But then the bureaucracy its
job was to
control and administer the the territory
which was captured. Its job was to
extract the resources.
It was to enforce the rule long after
the battles were over. So the British
Empire's real power, it was the
interaction between naval power in the
in the in the frontiers of the of the
empire and the bureaucracy in the
interior of the empire.
Right?
Krishna of the Suryam Netherlands says
in the book Indika by Meastanes
the Greek ambassador to partiput to
India. So in this book indica it's
mentioned that there were seven casts in
bhat bashra but it was better organized
than now with four casts. Does that also
correspond with our own indigenous
sources? What's my view on this? So
mastes was the Greek ambassador
to India.
Um he was based in Patutra present day
Patna.
Um and he wrote this treaties this book
about India about what he observed in
India what kind of society does India
have what kind of geography does India
have it was a very practical
book the kind of book that you will find
in a military tactical manual or
something
so one of the observations that Mastinis
made was that there were seven classes
of people in Indian society okay what
kind of people what classes of people
seven classes First of all, you had
philosophers or or wise men, okay, which
would include Brahmans and other
religious specialists. Their job was to
perform religious rituals and sometimes
advise the king. When you had farmers,
cultivators, uh they would produce food
obviously and they were not required to
participate in any war effort. Their job
was to only cultivate food which would
be something that serves the entire
society. Then you had herdsmen and
hunters, you know, people who uh who who
did animal husbandry who kept herds of
cattle or animals and also people who
hunted. Then you had traders and
artisan, craftsmen, merchants, people
who were engaged in production of goods
in the exchange of goods. Then you had
the warriors, soldiers, fighting men.
They were professional warriors. They
were distinct from other classes and
their job was to only prepare for war at
all times and be be prepared. Then you
had bureaucrats and overseers and
magistrates. Okay, officials,
inspectors, sometimes spies. Their job
was to supervise the administration of
the society of the of the government. Uh
their job was to supervise markets.
Their job was to maintain public orders.
Police also would have been part of
this. And then you had the king's
counselors and high officers. the people
who were involved in advising the king
and running the government at the high
level high levels and judging various
things. Okay. So that's the situation
that you had in India. Seven classes of
people and measures reported that there
was no there were no slaves in India.
There was no slavery in India. So
Mastanis classified Indian society into
seven classes based on the function that
people uh served in society.
Now does this correspond with our Indian
indigenous sources? So India's sources
don't mention seven classes of of people
in society. If you if you study various
Sanskrit texts, ancient texts from that
time period, other time periods, there's
no mention of seven classes of society.
The Indian texts emphasize jatis
innumerable jatis in Indian society
classified essentially into four vernas
four major categories of occupations but
uh innumerable jatis that's what our
texts emphasize the sevenfold division
is something that migastines came up
with he classified the occupations of
people classifi classified the functions
and he he came up with a seven-fold
classification, seven class scheme. So
Indian texts don't speak about this.
It's also possible that maybe Indian
texts did encode this information but
those texts were all destroyed because a
thousand years ago all of India's texts,
the majority of India's texts were
destroyed in the destruction of India's
libraries by the Turks and the burning
of the destruction of the universities
by the Turks and the burning of the
library. So maybe that information was
there but it was destroyed. But whatever
information we have today based on the
on the evidence and records that we have
today, there is no mention in Indian
texts of a sevenfold division of the
society in India.
Right. Okay.
Um
Sahaj Dang says, shouldn't India
shouldn't Sri Lanka be a part of India
instead of being a separate nation? So I
don't think I have to open the map to
show you where Sri Lanka is. I'm sure
all Indians know where Sri Lanka is. You
ought to know. Yeah. So the question is
shouldn't Sri Lanka be a part of India
instead of being a separate nation?
Well, let's go back to history. The
various historical periods in our
history and
place Sri Lanka in the context. If we
talk about the Morian period,
that's about 2,300 years ago roughly.
Chandra Gupta Moria Bindhuar Ashok and
so on and the
Morian Empire was it was at its greatest
extent during Emperor Ashok's time at
that time was Sri Lanka part of India
was Sri Lanka administered from
partiputra
it wasn't
was it a vasal possibly
but it wasn't part of the empire Empire.
If you talk about the subsequent great
empire, the Kushan Empire, was Sri Lanka
part of the Kushan Empire? It wasn't.
Next, you have the Gupta Empire. Huge,
vast empire. Was Sri Lanka ever a part
of the Gupta Empire?
As far as I can remember, it wasn't. But
let's fact check my memory. Um, let's
let's find out. Okay. Was Shri Lanka
part of the
Gupta Empire's
territory
let's see
so Sri Lanka was not a formal territory
of the Gupta Empire but it was a vasal
state of of the Gupta Empire there Sri
Lanka's ruler acknowledged the Gupta
emperor Samudra Gupta Suzaranti
so Sri Lanka was a vasal. It was not
officially formally part of India. It
wasn't Gupta Empire. Then the next great
empire is the Chola Empire. Rajendra
Chola whether it is Rajaraj or Rajendra
one of those two conquered Sri Lanka and
Sri Lanka was part of the official
territory the formal it was formally
part of the Chola Empire. So yes Chola
Empire Sri Lanka was part of India. Then
what's next? Marata Empire. Sri Lanka
was not part of the Maratha Empire.
British Raj, it was part of the British
Raj, but that's not an Indian Empire.
It's a conquest empire, right? It's a
it's it's a foreign occupying force. So
that we we don't discuss that. We're
talking about our history, not not the
history that foreigners imposed upon us.
So if we look at if you regard if we
examine all these different empires that
have ruled India that have been part of
our history our government our
administration apart from the Chola
Empire none of the other empires had
incorporated for Sri Lanka formally into
its territory.
So Sri Lanka is obviously part of the
subcontinental region. The Sri Lankan
people have the same genetics as us, the
same religious and and cultural and
civilizational heritage as us. They're
essentially the same people as us. The
language they speak is an is an arian
language, Indo-arian language.
Um, of course there is a sizable Tamil
population in Sri Lanka who speak Tamil,
but once again, same people, right? So
Sri Lanka
is is a nation that's essentially Indian
but it's a separate nation state. So
should Sri Lanka be a part of India? It
depends on the context. When Joseph
Stalin was shown a map of India, he
asked about he pointed to Sri Lanka and
said what is this island? And he was
told it's a separate country. He said
why is it a separate country? Are you
people crazy? So yeah from that
perspective if you are a great power you
should incorporate all territories that
you can.
So the situation today is such that
India isn't that powerful
right now. The situation is such that
the greatest
just like
the the most powerful nation in Western
Europe isn't Germany or France or
England. It's the United States. Even
though the US is geographically not part
of Europe, it is still the most powerful
entity,
the most powerful nation in Western
Europe. Similarly, today we have a
situation that the most powerful nation
in the Indian subcontinent isn't India,
it's the United States. And in that
situation, there's no way India can make
Sri Lanka part of the nation. Maybe in
the future if India becomes way more
powerful may happen. We'll see about
that.
So it's not about is it morally correct
for Sri Lanka to be part of India.
There's no morality in geopolitics.
It's all about can you do it? Are you
powerful enough to make it happen?
And India today is not powerful enough
to make it happen.
Okay. Um
Nirvana Shanks says, "What was the Wild
West? How did expansion, frontier life,
conflict of the Native Americans,
lawlessness, and economic opportunities
define this period in American history?
Okay, wild west. Let's go to the map and
I'm going to show you the river
Mississippi because it's going to be
well relevant to what we're going to
discuss here. So, once again, we go to
the to the to North America. Okay? And
let's search for the Mississippi River.
Mississippi River, United States.
It's giving me just one point.
Okay. Look, uh, the Mississippi River,
it drains out near Galveastston. I said,
no, New Orleans. Sorry. So, somewhere
here you have the drainage
basin of the Mississippi River.
Is it here? It's somewhere New Orleans,
obviously. So, is this the Mississippi?
Yeah, this is the Mississippi. So the
Mississippi River drains out into the
Gulf of Mexico
in the New Orleans region. Now if you go
north,
if you go to, for example, Minneapolis,
which is all the way north, Minneapolis,
Minnesota,
well, if you zoom in, which river do we
have here? It's the Mississippi.
Would you believe it? And the
Mississippi originates somewhere up here
up north. I'm not going to try and trace
out the origins. I once did that. This
is the Mississippi. It originates in a
lake or something up north here
somewhere here. So, it's a massive
gigantic river, the longest river system
in the world.
And it kind of divides the US into two
halves. Not two halves, but an eastern
part of the US and the western part of
the US. And the wild west was the region
west of the Mississippi River. Okay, so
that's the starting point of our
discussion. The Wild West was the part
the region of the US present US which
was west of the Mississippi River. So
that's the geographical context. But
what about the temporal context? What
time period are we talking about? Wild
west. We're talking about the
19th century. So the American Civil War
ended in 1865.
So from the time of the end of the Civil
War in the US 1865 to about 1900.
That's the kind that's the time period
we're talking about when we're talking
about the Wild West. So it was this
frontier region of the US west of the
Mississippi. And the frontier was always
pushing westwards, pushing westwards,
pushing westwards. Okay. Um so this
period between 1865 and 1900 is when
most of the western territories in the
US were settled
settled forcibly by the European origin
people. They were settled the
territories were grabbed they were
fenced up and then they were linked by
rail by railroads and roads and then
states were created.
For example Delaware Delaware is in the
east but yeah you get the point. These
states were created. So this period what
did you have in this period? You had
rapid westward expansion of European
colonizers, colonists, settlers. They
had to face harliving conditions because
there was no settlement there, European
settlement. And the the the Europeans
what they would do was that they had
guns and superior technology and they
would violently displace the Native
Americans from the Native American
territories which eventually became the
US West. Okay. And when you have this
going on, there is no there's no law.
There's no court of law. The territory
is unknown. There's very few Europeans
there. There's no one to give you law
and justice and police and all that. So
there was essentially no law which is
lawlessness.
But there were tremendous economic
opportunities because new land,
inexhaustible quantities of new land.
The land was rich in resources. You
could do mining in the land. much of the
land was good for mining. You could do
ranching, you know, agriculture on the
land, cattle, cattle ranching, you
ranching, you could raise cattle on
those on that land and you would link
everything through railroads. Okay. So
in the US government at the time the
government's policies
supported a transcontinental railroad
system and this encouraged millions of
European origin settlers to start moving
and pushing westwards and they were told
whatever territories you you you grab
they're yours essentially right so huge
vast areas of grasslands even deserts
were turned into farms and ranches and
eventually towns And people settled
there and the frontier line kept on
inexorably moving westwards, pushing
westwards. So new territories would be
surveyed, they would be settled, the
natives would be massacred or pushed
out, right? And then these territories
would eventually be turned into states
and eventually they pushed out all the
way to the Pacific Ocean in the west. So
life in the frontier for the Europeans
was pretty demanding. It was very
isolated. Small settlements. Yeah.
families would live in
um small cabins, small houses. They had
to cope with very extreme, very harsh
weather, extreme weather. Yeah. They had
to rely on farming essentially
subsistance farming. They had to rely on
hunting um or they had to initially rely
rely on small-cale ranching um and then
they eventually built up churches and
churches are very important for European
life at the at the time. and then local
committees and schools. Um and uh at
this time you also had something that
was a devastating event, man-made event
that was happening in the Americas,
North America, the the near destruction
of the American bison. So the Native
Americans, they depended, especially the
the so-called plains Indians in the
Great Plains regions, they depended on
the native on on the American bison for
everything.
The bison were called buffalo.
So their entire lifestyle, livelihood,
everything depended on the bison. They
depended on the bison for meat, for fur.
They depended on the bones of the bison,
for various things. Everything revolved
around the bison. So the Americans, the
Europeans, European occupiers decided,
let's kill off every single every last
bison. That way the entire lifestyle and
livelihood of the uh of the natives will
be wiped out and they will become
helpless. As long as the bison exist,
these people have all the power in the
world because they they get all the
food, all everything from the bison. If
the bison no longer exists, they will
become completely helpless and dependent
on us and then they'll be able to we'll
be able to make them do what we want. So
the Americans went out with rifles and
they just started randomly shooting
bisons. They killed million hundreds of
millions of bison and the American North
American bison was was nearly made
extinct.
So this was going on at the time of the
wild west expansion. Yeah. So all these
Native American population centers were
devastated.
The whites
seized land for mining, for ranching,
for settling. Whatever treaties they had
made with the natives were broken. And
then eventually they were able to
subjugate all the tribes, massacre them,
brutalize them, subjugate them and push
them onto reservations. Okay? And this
process obviously involved multiple wars
which were called the Indian wars. So
you had wars with these native tribes.
There were massacres all over the place.
There were forcible removals of people
from their territory and shoving them
into territories thousand hundreds of
kilometers away. Yeah, there was
resistance against the Europeans by
groups like the the Lacot, like the
Cheyenne
and the Europeans retaliated with
military campaigns and with policies
whose objective was to end the
indigenous control of the lands in North
America. So you had all of this
situation
and eventually they were able to start
you know settle down in towns, create
towns, have low enforcement
um and so on. But for a long time you
had a lawless state in in the the Wild
West. You had theft, you had uh cattle
theft, cattle rustling they called.
Sometimes you had big crimes and so on.
You had vigilant justice. You had groups
of people who would meet out justice.
They were called posies.
Um there are people who were hired as
low men to fill the gap. They would have
revolvers or guns or whatever. So
everyday life for the white residents,
white settlers would be about routine
disputes and so on, not the spectacular
gunfights that you see in in in
Hollywood movies.
So that's how how it was. And eventually
um what you found is that the the
Europeans were able to push further
westwards and settle. And this gave rise
to tremendous economic opportunities for
the Europeans. And this attracted a huge
population, very diverse population. You
had all kinds of European immigrants,
Germans and a and Dutch people and all.
You obviously had African-Americans,
slaves. You had Mexicans who would come
and work. You had Chinese workers who
had been imported and so on. And all of
this shaped the US economy, the US
demography.
And yeah, it was a time when you had
essentially full freedom. So the wild
west was all about individual freedom
and liberty and upward mobility.
That was the wild west in the US.
Amisha says, why weren't Native
Americans the primary slave population
in America?
Great question. The Native Americans
were the indigenous people who lived in
large numbers in the United States. Why
weren't they made the slaves? Why did
the Americans, the European colonizers,
occupiers, why did they import African
slaves? That's a great question. The
reason is simple. The natives had large
population groups. They could always
escape
and get refuge with one of these
population groups. Even if you had
different tribes, but they still all
regarded the white man as the as the
oppressor, as the occupier. And the
Native Americans, they knew the
geography of the region very well, of
the entire continent essentially. They
were very well adapted for thousands of
years to the climate.
So it was very hard to control them and
they were very good at escaping. And if
they escaped, they would they would be
fine. They would not die out. If an
African origin slave escaped, he
essentially faced almost certain death.
The Africans were not adapted to the
climate. They did not understand the
geography of the region. They would be
either recaptured or they would just die
from exposure to the to the elements,
the climate.
Um,
it's not like Native Americans weren't
enslaved. Native Americans were also
enslaved. But eventually the Europeans
decided that the African slaves were a
better investment,
right? And eventually the natives were
massacred and their populations declined
drastically.
So it made sense to have Africans come
and Africans were sturdier and maybe
more reliable slaves. So a combination
of these factors
ensured that the it was lucrative and
and and
seen as a good investment to have
African slaves instead of enslaving
large numbers of native Americans.
Natives were also enslaved in large
numbers but eventually Africans were
preferred because of these reasons.
Okay, let's take maybe a couple more
questions. Um
this is an interesting one really now
says why do you think the US had so many
successful psycho serial killers between
the 1970s and 1990s so the so-called
golden age of serial killers 3600
killers I'm not sure about that number
definitely around a thousand maybe
slightly less than thousand 36 seems a
little inflated but whatever so you had
the golden age of serial killers
way more serial serial killers than any
other country even after considering per
capita and high reporting numbers. Also,
do US cops get away with almost
anything? So, the US is the nation that
essentially invented serial killers. I
think I mean nowhere else have you had
so many serial killers? Like the US I
mean the names are kind of legendary in
the nastiest of ways. John Wayne Gasey,
um Ted Bundy, and and so many more.
Okay, so these these folks, I mean,
these people were just inhuman monsters,
and some of them had had,
you know, the number of people they
killed went into the hundreds, some of
them.
Um, so why was this this this the case?
You had there are reports of serial
killers of other nations too.
Um you had one very infamous serial
killer in the USSR. I forget his name.
Uh who was pretty monstrous but it's the
US that has given the world this entire
thing. Serial killer. So why why did you
have this situation?
So many serial killers all the way from
the 1970s to the 1990s. So the US is an
artificial nation. It's been settled by
foreigners, right, by Europeans. And
much of the US is just wide open, very
low population density. So in the from
the 1950s, the Wild West era was from
the 19 from the from from 1865 all all
the way to 1900. The Indians were
properly subjugated. The Indians as in
the Native Americans were properly
subjugated around 1900 or so. You still
had a few more rebellions, but by the
time the the the west was mainly
conquered, but the west was still the
west the west of the Mississippi was
still, you know, um it still had a very
low population density. And then by the
1950s, you had the explosion of
suburbia, which which means suburban
neighborhoods, wide open neighborhoods
with low population density, where you
have all these houses, the baby boomers
set up houses there. So you had low
population density, you had the
explosion of suburbs, you had high
mobility, you had highways all across
the country. So people traveling all the
time. So it was not unusual for you to
meet strangers.
Most of the people very often you would
meet would be strangers. That's one.
Then you had
from the 1950s60s onwards socializing
became an outdoor kind of activity.
people would spend time socializing in
in bars in pubs or whatever
and over there you would meet a lot of
strangers. So it was not unusual at all
to meet a person you've never seen
before and you would not feel
uncomfortable at that time. You also had
um rudimentary policing methods. You do
not have uh databases of serial killers
of or criminals. You do not have
fingerprint databases. You do not have
DNA databases. The techn the DNA
fingerprinting technology did not even
exist at the time. So
because of these factors
and and you had mercury,
you had lead in petrol in gasoline. So
there was a time when there used to be a
lot of lead in the gasoline petrol in
the US and that damages people's brains
and causes criminal tendencies
apparently. So combination of these
factors created you know high level of
criminality in the in the United States.
and the rise of serial killers
and uh then serial kill this entire
phenomenon of serial killer became a
popular fiction etc kind of theme and
those stories that would come out in
literature and popular fiction and and
TV series they would then serve as
templates for new serial killers to for
how to execute their whatever they were
executing you know their methodology.
So because of this from the 1960s '7s
onwards all the way through to the 1990s
you had this proliferation of these evil
psychotic
monsters serial killers all across the
United States some of whom are very
famous or rather infamous and from the
1990s onwards you had the United States
had constructed this database of
criminals with their fingerprints
eventually DNA DNA information data all
of that and and policing methods became
more and more sophisticated
So from the '90s onwards it was it
became and then you had the
proliferation of of uh CCTV cameras and
then with the advent of cell phones it
was it became easy to track anybody. Uh
because of all these factors eventually
technology caught up and then it was it
became very hard for anyone to be a
serial killer which is why you have you
have so few serial killers today and
even if you have serial killers uh they
don't
you know they don't have too many
victims before they caught. So that was
the phase the US went through and it
essentially is is the nation that
invented serial killers more or less.
All right. Um let's take maybe one or
two more questions. Um I still have so
many questions to take but uh we have
gone way past two hours so I'll take
maybe one or two more. Real Vladimir
Putin says lot of industry lots of
industry lists in India date back their
family business all the way to British
occupation of India. It is clear that
these industry lists were on the British
payroll. What's my opinion? How did they
get all the wealth? Look
during the British occupation of India
if you were an industrialist you had to
cooperate with the British in all ways
in every way. You could only become
successful if you had the blessings of
the British.
Essentially, you could only be
successful as an industrialist, as a
business person, if you were a British
collaborator,
which means you acted or you colluded
with the British against against the
interests of India.
As simple as that.
It may be hard to believe for some of
you because of the indoctrination you've
got through the education system.
Imagine this different scenario.
1940s France
occupied by Nazi Germany. France in the
1940s was under Nazi Germany's
occupation. Fully controlled by the Nazi
Germany by by Nazi Germany.
The French government the Vishy regime
was a puppet government. It was entirely
controlled by the Germans during this
time period. If a French business was
successful, what would it mean? It means
that they colluded with the with the
German occupiers.
Otherwise, the Germans would never allow
any business to succeed in France unless
it colluded and cooperated and
collaborated with the Nazi occupiers.
Makes sense, right? Now that I give this
example,
but when I give the example of India,
you're like, "No, no, no, never
happened. It cannot happen." Every
single successful Indian business
that operated during the British
occupation of India
was able to succeed by colluding and
collaborating with the British against
the interests of India.
As simple as that. And many of these
businesses still kind of are big
businesses today. So anyone who was
wealthy in 1947
was wealthy only because of collusion
with the British. Because in 1857
the British destroyed India's
authentic royal families and they
plundered all the wealth from every
single rich wealthy person who had
become wealthy legitimately.
without colluding with foreigners.
After 1857, if you are wealthy, it means
that you had colluded with the British.
As simple as that.
They did not allow a single wealthy
person to remain wealthy unless they
were colluding with them in unless they
were of some value to the British. That
is a very harsh truth that you we have
to understand.
Everybody colluded with the British. All
those who are wealthy. Anybody who was
wealthy in 1947 was a collaborator.
That's it. It's the truth.
Okay. Okay. I'm going to end this here.
Maybe I can Let's see the live chat.
What do we have? We have 21 super chats.
We have 21 super chats. Well, okay.
I shall take those.
That's going to take another one hour.
Let's see. Okay. My request is please
stop taking superhat so that I can end
this live stream at at a reasonable
time. Okay. Let's see this. Chakraat
says, "How much did the Marshall plan
really drive Europe's
re-industrialization
and how fair is the belt and road
comparison about US companies benefiting
completely?"
Marshall plan. It's been a while since
I've thought about the Marshall Plan.
I'm a little fuzzy on that right now,
sir.
The Marshall Plan, obviously, it did
drive Europe's industrialization, but it
made Europe beholden to the US in a
variety of ways. Now, how exactly did
that happen? I'm going to have to do
some refreshing of my
of my memory before I can tell you about
that. Right now, I don't have an answer
on the spot. It's been a while since
I've read about this,
a long while. So yeah, I cannot answer
this question as of now on the spot
about the Marshall plan, but maybe I
will revisit it in the future.
It's Anjay Anjay says, "If Mr. Trump can
move on with invasion with an invasion
via BS excuses, shouldn't Mr. Modi go
for a Pakistan? Are we so weak that we
can't even
monkey big boss?" See, my friends, let
me show you a harsh truth about the
world. It may upset many many many of
you but
my job over here is to tell you the
truth so that you understand the world
better. So
here's the map of the world. You see
first of all let's see Western Europe.
Which is the most powerful nation in
Western Europe? It's the United States.
Even though the US is all the way across
the Atlantic, the US is the most
powerful nation in Western Europe. None
of these countries can do anything
significant without taking permission
from the United States. Similarly, in
the Indian subcontinent,
the most powerful nation isn't India. It
is the United States. If Mr. Modi goes
for East Pakistan, the US will
India's economy without firing a single
bullet through economic sanctions. That
is the harsh truth. Is it Mr. Modi's
fault? It's not Mr. Modi's fault. Mr.
The Modi has been doing whatever he can
since 2014 and we have come a long way.
But if we had started in 1948 47 or even
in 1990
today we would be able to make a move on
East Pakistan. Right now we can't. It is
what it is. That's just the facts. ICMBB
says can you speak a little about why
Chinese civil wars feature a lot more in
top 10 deadliest conflicts? Is there a
philosophical reasoning behind it? No,
there's no philosophical reasoning
behind it.
There's a part of China that is
immensely populated. The population
density is very high. It's called the
Hihei Taong line. Let me show you that.
Um, okay. See, here it is.
Teng Chong Hi Ten Chong line. See,
check out this this division. The yellow
portion is about 5% of China's
population, 6%.
And the red portion is 94% of China's
population. Very high population
density. Now historically even the
northern part of the red zone wasn't
China. It's only the southern half of
the red zone which was Han China and
most of your conflicts happened there.
Okay. These conflicts were part of
China's imperial cycles. In a in a
Chinese imperial cycle, you have a
dynasty that rises. it it becomes
powerful. It creates an empire. It has
the mandate of heaven. Eventually, it
loses the mandate of heaven which means
it it loses control of the country and
then it collapses and there's a period
of 50 or 100 years maybe of 200 years of
just chaos and civil war.
And this civil war is it happens in
population centers and whatnot. Which is
why you have extremely high casualties,
extremely high 50 million dead, 20
million dead. that that that that sort
of number numbers that boggle your
imagination.
So that that's how it is in China.
Chinese conflicts are typically just
mind-boggling in scale and
and it's also something to do with
culture. Right? In India, you've never
had civil wars. And even when you had
conflicts between kingdoms, the
conflicts would never involve citizens,
civilians never
because of the way India society is
structured civilizationally. But it's
only warriors who fight and you never
touch civilians. In China, there was no
such thing. So everybody got involved
and dragged into the whole thing. And
that's why you had massive, massive
casualties, siege warfare, starvation,
poisoning of water, cannibalism,
whatnot.
Shivanchu
Dadich says, "Where can I learn about
Vidanta or Sanka or Hindu philosophy?
What are the authentic sources?" I am
not the right person to ask this. If you
want a book reference, I can give you
one. Uh Indian philos who is Indian
philosophy.
An introduction introduction to
Indian philosophy.
The book is by Oh yeah, this one uh this
one this one book by Satish Chandra
Chhatji
and introduction to Indian philosophy I
would recommend this book this is a good
introductory introduction
to Indian philosophy
uh it's in English obviously
this is what I can recommend beyond that
I I I don't know I am not an expert in
vanta or shanka or Hindu philosophy
But this book gives you a good decent
introduction highlevel introductory
introduction into Hindu philosophy. We
also have book books by Max Zimmer.
I'm sure I've referred to those books in
the past on this channel. There's also
the principle of byopran
and so on. I would say the book that I
showed you that that's a good way to get
introduced to Hindu philosophy.
Dva Koshel says why has India not
considered a China Pakistan economic
corridor style trade corridor with China
or Russia Russian aircraft
instead of relying on Boeing and Airbus?
What does CPEC have to do with Boeing
and Airbus?
Okay, it's two questions you're asking
me, separate questions. Why has India
not considered a CPEC style trade
corridor with China? China is an
adversary nation. China seeks India's
balkcanization.
China agrees with the US only on one
thing. India must not rise. How can we
have a China Pakistani that sort of
corridor with with China? Especially
when we have a hundred billion dollar
trade deficit with them, they will empty
our treasury even more. Simply can't
happen.
Why isn't India buying Chinese weapons?
Tell me. Because China is an adversary.
China won't ever sell it. Certainly
weapons. So immediately China will never
agree to a trade corridor with India
unless it is in their benefit. If it's
in their benefit, it's going to hurt us.
Makes no sense, sir.
Um why hasn't India considered Russian
aircraft instead of relying on Boeing
and Airbus? Because Boeing and Airbus
are western and they are better and
superior.
Yeah.
I mean does Russia have an answer to
Boeing or Airbus? Which aircraft does
President Putin travel in? Which
aircraft
does Putin travel in?
So it is an illusion.
It's an illusion. IL96.
What's it look like? Yeah, it's a good
one, isn't it?
But the issue is that they don't have
the best engines. But if it is good
enough for Vladimir Putin, I suppose it
should be good enough for um ordinary
people. Uh but overall Boeing and Airbus
have better aircraft overall. The
Russians have kind of fallen slightly
behind in these matters. The engines
that they use, the western aircraft like
the Rolls-Royce engines etc., those are
high quality engines, extremely good
fuel efficiency and so on. the the the
the Russian aircraft have historically
been known for being
fuel guzzlers
and Russia had this great aircraft
industry. Illusian, Tupolev,
um
Berv, so many different manufacturers,
Sukoy obviously, Mikoyan, Gurvich,
I'm not sure what the status is right
now. We have signed a deal with with
Sukoy, right? the Suk Sukoy Super 100
aircraft or something it's called which
is an aircraft with about which can
carry about 100 passengers we're going
to manufacture those in India that's
great so if the Russians can make high
quality aircraft will be it will be
great for India to co-manufacture those
or even you know have some kind of
arrangement agreement through which you
can buy those or manufacture those in
India but overall right now as of now at
least the western aircraft are superior
and India loves western stuff right So
yeah, but it's a it's a good suggestion.
It's a great suggestion. We should
explore Russian alternatives to Western
offerings.
Godliness says rule-based order and UN
resolutions are for weaklings, but the
big big eagle, dragon, and bear can do
whatever they want. What about Taiwan
now? That's a good question. What about
Taiwan now? What happens now? So the
Chinese had the past few days encircled
Taiwan and done unprecedented live
firing exercises and naval exercises,
air force exercises around Taiwan.
Essentially encircling the island and
some people interpreted this as a
warning to the US. If you take
Venezuela, we'll take Taiwan. Well,
Venezuela is done. What happened to
Taiwan? I don't see any move by China on
Taiwan because Taiwan is not that easy.
Taiwan is in China's backyard but China
can't take it. I think they have a
deadline right Xiinping has given a
deadline. President Shi has given a
deadline to his armed forces PLA that by
2027 Taiwan must be reintegrated. We'll
see about that.
Now Venezuela is done. Regime change has
been effected. Soon you will have that
Nobel Prize winning lady who will be
sitting in the hot seat in Venezuela as
a puppet just like Muhammad Yus sits in
East Pakistan. That sort of thing.
So Venezuela has done. Now what about
Iran?
What if the US makes a move on Iran?
Similar to what they've done in
Venezuela, will China move make a move
on Taiwan then? Because the longer China
waits and the more of these pieces fall
into the US lap, the weaker China gets
gets and the fewer options it has it
has. So yeah, I think the world is the
temperature is rising now. What about
Taiwan now? Well, that depends on
President Xanping. Does he have the
gumption to order
the PLA to go ahead and make a move?
We'll see about that. I think it's still
that that's a big call to make that espe
essentially plunges the world into war.
It can be very damaging to China's
economy. China can't afford that right
now. That's where we are. I think
Xiinping can't make a move on Taiwan
right now.
That's where we are.
Birup Sharkar says, "Has the quality of
US diplomacy declined? In the 80s, they
coordinated with Saudi Arabia to drive
drive down oil prices and strain the
USSR's economy. They seem unable to
replicate a similar strategy today."
See, diplomacy is an extension of
warfare and warfare is an extension of
diplomacy.
Diplomacy sounds very nice and
sophisticated and polite on camera.
Behind closed doors, diplomacy is
brutal. Diplomacy is outright threats.
arm twisting of the worst kind, the
worst kind of threats and so on.
Diplomacy is nasty, nasty stuff. So it's
the same thing as war but by different
means as the quality of US diplomacy
declined. Why diplomacy if it goes hand
inhand with military action has been
very successful. They've taken Venezuela
out. Um in the 80s they did this with
Saudi Arabia drown to drive down oil
prices to strain USSR's economy.
seem unable to replicate a similar
strategy today. They don't seek to do
such a thing today.
If they drive oil prices down, it's
going to hurt everybody.
And oil prices are
they they are well, unless you do
something artificial like what they did
at the time, oil prices are market
driven. And if you artificially mess
mess around with the oil prices, it's
going to mess up the entire global
economy. It's going to have second
order, third order effects that you
don't want.
It may end up hurting the US. The US
dollar is still the petro dollar. Yeah,
it it depends on oil prices for its
legitimacy on it depends on oil oil
supply for for its legitimacy. Um I
don't think the US even seeks to drive
oil prices down right now. If they want
they can but they don't want to. So,
okay. Two kilowatts photographer says,
"I dreamt that you met Modi G in an
exhibition." All right. Okay. Nice
dream. Um, I have come face to face with
Mr. Modi on on several occasions. The
last time was during the G20 summit in
2023.
But yeah, I haven't met him in person
like you know onetoone meeting that that
hasn't happened. But nice nice dream you
had. May it come true.
Okay.
Our opinion channel says 18 year old 60
1381 elo. Oh, chess. That's a good
rating. Education feels like a
suffocating factory. Father says it's
too late for chess. Chess mastery or
degree for survival. Please help. Got
passion.
Well, that's a tough choice, right? Uh
dad says it's too late for chess. You're
18 years old.
Why is it too late for chess if you're
18?
Um 1381 elo rating is a good rating.
Education obviously is suffocating. We
understand.
I would say ideally do both. Get your
degree so your dad doesn't nag you too
much and in the free time in your free
time keep doing chess. Don't let it let
let the flame of chess die away.
Or if you think you're really good
enough for chess, then well
the option is to take a risk. But risks
are risky and I am not the right person
who can suggest take a risk. I don't
know how good you are at chess. I don't
know what your potential is in chess. If
you have if if I I will see if
hypothetically I see that you have the
potential to be a top 20 player globally
in chess, I would say dump everything
and go for it. But I don't know where
you stand in chess. Let me see what does
3081 ELO rating mean? Um 13
81 ELO rating.
How good is that? Intermediate to solid
beginner intermediate level placing you
above average in many online chess
platforms like chess.com but below
expert levels. Okay.
So you fall into a game's gold or
advanced tier systems.
Okay. Above average, you're past
beginner. You're intermediate. You're
consistently challenging players in that
range.
For official feeder rankings, 1381 is a
specific numerical value, but context
matters and so on. So, it's a solid
rating, but
you're definitely not a beginner. You're
intermediate. Solid rating, but I don't
know you personally. So, I don't know if
if you have the potential for being, you
know, at at the top in the top elite
ranks in chess. If you have the
potential to be an elite chess player,
well then your
financial security essentially can be
taken care of by that.
So in case you are that good, maybe
chess is the right move. Otherwise,
get your degree and continue chess.
That's what I'll say. All right, sir.
I understand how you feel. I've been
there.
Anyway, all the best. All the best, sir.
Do well, make the right choice.
Godliness says a lot of Pakistani PTI
leaders and many Indian columnists
believe Operation Zindur helped Aim
Munir a lot. He is now more powerful and
dangerous. Your view, it is the US that
helped Aim Mader.
It's the US. The US
needs Pakistan as a counterbalance to
India and Operation Tindur had to
happen. Do you please please understand
after they do a terror attack like the
kind of like the kind that did
we had to respond otherwise we lose our
credibility as a as a as a serious
nation. Do you understand?
If we don't respond India looks like
a loser, a punching bag all over again.
we had no choice but to respond
and that gave the US the opportunity to
elevate a similar status.
So once this happened, once the
terrorist attack happened, we had no
choice. We had to do what we had to what
we did. So you can't blame Modi for
this, right?
That's my view.
Uh BJU Saka says, "My hot take is that
the 2030s is going to be China's best
but last chance to beat the US in terms
of GDP. After the 30s, the median age
will be around 45 to 48 to 50 years. The
population will also decline heavily.
China is going to keep rising.
See my view, my hottake,
China is going to keep rising
economically
and technologically
until the late 2030s, mid 2040s.
That's when the decline of China will
begin because then the median age will
be above 50.
So it kind of aligns with your hottake.
But will China be able to beat the US in
terms of GDP?
GDP is okay. What China needs to beat
the US in is technology
and predominance in East Asia.
If China can dislodge the US from East
Asia, if China can break out of the
island trains,
that's a gigantic victory for for China.
If China can break out into the Pacific,
the Chinese Navy. So all of that, the
best chance will be well
this decade actually this decade and the
longer China waits, the tougher it's
going to get for China. GDP is okay. It
is
the geographical
confinement of China that makes China
weak through the three island chains
first, second, third island chain. Uh
the GDP is okay man even with a lower
GDP if you have a powerful military you
can do wonders. So that's how I see it.
Kiran Mor says any updates on Nepal, Sri
Lanka and Bhutan? No, right now no
updates on Nepal, Sri Lanka, Bhutan.
Uh Vijua says why did big daddy US allow
Brexit to happen? Because they wanted
you the UK out of the EU orbit and they
wanted the UK to be a special lap dog
for themselves. That's why Sid Barka
says US captured Moduro a special
military operation. Absolutely. It's a
special military operation ordered by
Shri Donald Trump. If the US does it,
it's good. It's for human rights. It's
for democracy. It's for the Nobel Peace
Prize winner. for putting her in the in
the in the seat of the leader of
Venezuela. It's all good if the US does
it. If Russia does it, very bad.
Okay. Godliness says it is Iran next.
Also, your view on how we should manage
our relationship with all with this
power-drunk US establishment. Both
Trump, MAGA and Democrats want Modi out.
Who is getting Nobel in India? Is Iran
next? Well, logically Iran should be
next.
Logically, Iran would be next. The
Western Hemisphere is settled now.
Whichever nations are slightly, you
could say, anti-US, they are
insignificant. Venezuela was the big
prize, but 1/5if of the entire world's
proven oil reserves. That's done. Next,
logically, it's Iran. Ukraine can wait.
Ukraine settlement can wait.
Yeah. So, the question is, what does
Russia do about it? What does China do
about it? Okay. How should we manage our
relationship with the US?
Manage it.
The only solution India has, only
option, only solution
is to keep quiet, absorb all the pain,
all the insults and work on the economy.
No master stroke reactions, no hard
harsh words, nothing. Just shut up and
do your job. That's it. That is the only
solution India has. 20 years of pain and
growth. Keep growing 6 7 8% per year
ideally 10% per year. That's all. That's
the only thing India can do. There is no
other option. We should have started
this process 20 years before it started.
Not in 19 not in 2014 but in 1994.
So this is where we are now.
So we have no option.
Uh yeah, everyone wants Modi out. We
know that who's getting nowhere in
India. I don't know.
Uh
AJ Aaya,
thank you very much sir. Ajit thank you
very much.
Biju Sakya says it's just a fun fact
that shocked me today.
Zoroastras Buddha confucious were all
alive at the same time. We are not quite
sure of that. I'm not sure about the
real date of the Buddha.
Goautam Buddha. I think there's a very
high chance that our ancient chronology
is just completely wrong. Zoroaster once
again we're not quite sure when he
lived. We're not sure.
Probably after the reign of Kurush Cyrus
the great because Cyrus was not
Zoroastrian. His descendants were but
once again is that the right time period
we not 100% sure. And Buddha
about two and a half millennia ago but
there's lots of question marks actually
about the sheet anchors of India's
history so
Nirut Kumar says Venezuela is about to
be made America's oil producing puppet
or colony like the US why doesn't India
do the same with Saudi Qatar who have
its oil own oil colony or
and have its own oil colony perpet
Well, we could do it if we had the
power.
We could do it if we had the power to do
it.
We don't.
We aren't powerful enough to do this at
this point in time. Why doesn't China
take Taiwan? China is so powerful.
Taiwan is right next door. Why doesn't
China take Taiwan? Because the US is too
powerful for it. Similarly, India, why
doesn't India take Qatar Saudi? Because
the Americans are too powerful. They
will not allow this to happen. We live
in the real world, right? That's why
uh V4 says, "You rock, thank you very
much, V4 Valor. Thank you so much for
your kind words and your encouragement.
I shall rock more." Thank you.
G L Haha says, "Please summarize the
situation in Venezuela. Why US bully
them?" I gave a half an hour summary at
the very beginning of this live stream.
So when the live stream ends, please go
ahead and watch it. I've summarized as
as best as I can and as in as much
detail as is possible at this early
stage
in the regime change operation. Okay.
Um Lolha says chat GPD disagrees with
this. Persia itself was part of an
ancient Vic culture then separated out
into Zorastan etc. their language roots
to ancient Indian language they will not
agree with it. So JPT is not evil. It's
just a poor AI system that somebody
controls.
Whatever inputs they have given to it,
it's going to respond to you based on
those inputs. And there may be some
subtle biases coded into it. So it's
okay.
It's okay. When India makes its own AI
systems, it they will agree with with
us. This is a foreign AI system. It's
Chad Japet's masters are sitting in the
US. So it's going to do what it's told.
The day India makes an indigenous AI
system, you will get better responses.
Maybe hopefully someday it happens.
UMXG Lha says Trump says US will run
Venezuela until proper puppet
installation thoughts. When will the
world finally get peace from it from
this nasty country, the US? Look, the US
could rule the world for another 200
years. Possibly. It's possible. So, I
can't say. Um Trump says the US will
rule Venezuela until proper propet
installation. Yeah, of course. What else
do you expect? That's how a regime
change operates. So the US has removed
the president. They've abducted the
president and his wife. They've taken
them somewhere. They'll be put through a
fair trial or whatever and they'll spend
years or years and years behind bars. So
that is done. Now somebody has to rule
Venezuela now or run Venezuela. So the
Americans will run Venezuela until that
Nobel Prize winning lady lady is brought
in as the puppet. Until that time, this
is the this is how the situation will
proceed. No big surprise here. Prattab
VGM says how Russia and China are even
allowed it to happen. The US is more
powerful than Russia plus China put
together.
The US affected a regime change in
Bangladesh. How did India allow this to
happen? Because the US is way more
powerful than India.
The US is sitting on Taiwan.
China wants Taiwan back. Why can't China
take it back? Because the US is way more
powerful than China.
That's how. Okay.
Okay.
Uh Brown Leprechaun says, "Joke. You
have put so much oil and food that
America wants to invade you. Be careful
about the oil and food. Be careful.
Yeah, indeed.
Jior TV says Trump says US will control
Venezuela until a transition is done and
will not allow anyone else to control
it. Absolutely.
Now this
territory belongs to the US. So the US
will control Venezuela until a
transition is done to a US installed
puppet who will control Venezuela. So
whatever happens, the US controls
Venezuela now. So, the US controls 20%
of the world's proven oil reserves and
nobody else will be allowed to control
it. Done deal. Outstanding.
Jorah TV says, "In my opinion, actions
in Venezuela may be a strategic move to
choke China's energy. Could Iran be
next? Is the US preparing for China
Taiwan crisis increasing the risk of a
major US China clash by 2026?"
Uh like I explained in great exhaustive
detail, Venezuela is home to about 1/5
of the entire world's proven oil
reserves. About between 65 to 80% of
Venezuela's oil the past 5 years has
gone to China. But that accounts for
only roughly 3% of China's oil imports.
So even if no more Venezuelan oil goes
to China, it will only affect about 3%
roughly of China's oil imports. The
majority of China's oil imports come
from Russia, which is 15 to 20% of
China's imports, and Saudi Arabia,
another 15 to 20% of China's imports.
Then you have nations like Angola and
Iraq and so on and so forth, who account
for the rest of China's oil imports. So
by cutting off Venezuela's supply to
China, it hardly does makes a dent in
China's oil imports. But Iran, if that
happens, well, that's going to be a
problem for China. So yeah, it's
possible that the US may go for Iran
next. Now that Venezuela is done and
dusted, makes sense to go for Iran next.
And that is obviously linked to Taiwan.
And if Iran is taken over and they are
able to create Somali land and South
Sudan that chokes off Babal Mandib the
straight of Babal Mandib in the Red Sea
Gulf of Aen if they can take Iran and
you can choke off Hormuz well then China
can can be starved of oil. So it looks
like the temperature globally is rising
geopolitically and there could be a
higher chance of a major China US clash
in 2026. Indeed,
the rational reporter says, "I believe
while China is our primary adversary now
due to proximity, the US will be the
real endgame. The US is far more stable.
What do I what do I think?" I completely
don't disagree with you at all.
All right, sir. And that brings me to
the end of today's live stream. Nearly 3
hours, very interesting.
So thank you so much everybody for the
questions and uh this situation is
evolving. So we're going to
continue this discussion tomorrow in
tomorrow's liveream and I look forward
to hear hearing from you and taking your
questions tomorrow. Until then take
care, keep asking questions, keep
raising your standards and I'll see you
in tomorrow's live stream. Take care.